<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religions peace: or, A plea for liberty of conscience. Long since presented to King James, and the High Court of Parliament then sitting, / by Leonard Busher citizen of London, and printed in the year 1614. Wherein is contained certain reasons against persecution for religion, also a designe for a peaceable reconciling of those that differ in opinion.</title>
            <author>Busher, Leonard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E334_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200599</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861307</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861307</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E334[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religions peace: or, A plea for liberty of conscience. Long since presented to King James, and the High Court of Parliament then sitting, / by Leonard Busher citizen of London, and printed in the year 1614. Wherein is contained certain reasons against persecution for religion, also a designe for a peaceable reconciling of those that differ in opinion.</title>
                  <author>Busher, Leonard.</author>
                  <author>H. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Sweeting at the Angel in Popes-head-alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes "To the Presbyterian reader", signed: H.B.</note>
                  <note>License to print on verso of first leaf.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April 25".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:113439:1"/>
            <p>THis uſefull Treatiſe (Entituled <hi>Religions Peace</hi>) long ſince Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by a Citizen of <hi>London</hi> to King <hi>JAMES,</hi> and the High Court of Parliament then ſitting; I allow to be Reprinted.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aprill</hi> 1.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Bachiler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RELIGIONS PEACE: OR, A PLEA for Liberty of Conſcience. Long ſince preſented to King <hi>James,</hi> and the High Court of Parliament then ſitting, by <hi>Leonard Buſher</hi> Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> and Printed in the Yeare 1614. Wherein is contained certain Reaſons againſt Perſecution for Religion; Alſo a deſigne for a peaceable reconciling of thoſe that differ in opinion.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 14.5, 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>One man eſteemeth one day above another, another man eſteemeth every day a like, let every man be fully perſwaded in his own minde.</p>
               <p>But why doſt thou judge thy brother, or why doſt thou deſpiſe thy brother? for we ſhall all appeare before the judgement ſeat of Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Sweeting</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Popes-head-alley,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113439:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113439:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>Presbyterian Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatiſe, which as a ſupplication to King <hi>James,</hi> and the Parliament, was Printed in the yeare <hi>1614.</hi> is for your good now againe re-printed, the Author thereof <hi>Leonard Buſher</hi> (an honeſt and godly Man, as I make no doubt will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to you in the peruſall of his Booke) intended two things therein.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to make it appeare that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were not true Miniſters, or ſucceſsive from the Apoſtles, but rather a Siens, or branch of the Popiſh ſtocke, deſcended from the Romiſh Hierarchy, to whom they owned their Inſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Ordination, and Function: Had this advice been believed and embraced by the Parliament then, the miſchiefes they have ſince practiſed much of the blood that hath been ſhed, and the miſeries that by their meanes have been brought upon us, had in great meaſure been prevented; but his Counſell was then ſlighted, though by the wiſdome of this preſent Parliament put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby we are ſecured for the future from the domination, compulſion againſt Conſcience, and notorious cruelties of that ſort of men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:113439:3"/>Whence we may learne, that what to a people at one time ſeemes ſtrange and abſurd, and in no wiſe to be admitted of, at another time appeares an acceptable truth; the reaſon is, becauſe wee are not Maſters of our owne underſtandings, but ſuffer them to bee dull'd and corrupted, till miſery, and the ſting of oppreſsion opens our eyes, ſo that we embrace truth more out of neceſsity then choice.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing his Diſcourſe drives at, is to make it appeare by Scriptures and ſound Arguments, that the onely way to make a Nation happy, and preſerve the People in love, peace and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, is to give liberty to all to ſerve God according as they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded is moſt agreeable to his Word; to ſpeake, write, print peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and without moleſtation in behalf of their ſeverall Tenets, and wayes of Worſhip (wholſome and pertinent Laws being made, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on penalties, to reſtrain all kinde of vice or violence, all kinds of reproach, ſlander, or injury either by word or deed;) And though this advice likewiſe ſeemes not the beſt to ſome, eſpecially to you my Brethren in the Presbyterian way, yet am I well aſſured that this Nation will never be happy; but as hitherto it hath been, ſo for the future it will be diſtracted with oppreſsion and perſecution, and the faces of one ſort of men ſet againſt another, till liberty of Conſcience be allowed. Indeed a man would thinke we had beene ſchool'd and whiſt long enough to it by our calamities, for went whereof this age, and that age, and the other age, and every age hath been miſerable. For want whereof the Apoſtles ſuffered mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, the Saints and godly of all times have been hunted like Patridges by birds of Prey: And yet, good men, in the eſteem of a great part of the world, eſpecially of the rich and powerfull they have ſuffered as evill-doers, diſturbers of the World, Heretiques, Schiſmaticks, ſeditious Perſons; and thoſe that put them to death, have had the reputation of being maintainers of Truth, and ſound Doctrine; ſo apt in all ages have the people been to miſtake good for evill, and evill for good.</p>
            <p>The Plea for liberty of Conſcience is no new Doctrine, as old certainly as the bleſſed Word of God it ſelfe, which gives us this
<pb facs="tcp:113439:3"/>
unmovable foundation thereof, That every Man ſhould bee fully perſwaded of the truth of that way wherein hee ſerves the Lord: And though there has been ſtruglings in all ages to make good this bleſſed birthright to all peacefull People, yet through thePotency and ſubtlety of Popes, Biſhops, and Miniſters that preferred the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of themſelves, and their uſurped and abuſed Function, before the good and welfare of the People; we have been deprived of this bleſsing, next to the manifeſtation of Gods love and goodneſſe to us, the moſt excellent and deſirable in this world: for want wherof, and by means of its contrary, Perſecution; this Vniverſe, eſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Chriſtian part thereof, hath ſuffered continuall agony and earthquake. Warres, and its miſeries have overſpread all Lands, States have been ſhaken and ſubverted Love, meekneſſe, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, mercy, (the trueſt badges of Chriſtianity) have been damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and baniſhed; and in their roomes cruelty, hardheartedneſſe, reſpect of Perſons, Priſons, tortures, &amp;c. things that our bleſſed Lord and Maſter, and his Apoſtles never prov'd, unleſſe upon their own afflicted bodies, have had great ſway for theſe many hundred yeares. Hence is it that in ſtead of Peace, we have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently had the Sword, in ſtead of ſweet tranquillity, love and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; hatred, contention, diſaffection, and the bitter fruits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath reign'd amongſt us, and in all probability will reigne till God ſhall put it into the heart of the Parliament to make tryall for prevention thereof, of this God-like way, which in the enſuing Treatiſe is held forth.</p>
            <p>I hope upon peruſall thereof, you that are my Brethren of the Presbyterian way, will abate much of your miſguided eagerneſſe in proſecuting your conſcientious Brethren. Conſider I beſeech you St. <hi>Paul</hi> before his converſion, he was as zealous I make no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as any of you, when he perſecuted the Saints, and <note n="(a)" place="margin">Acts <hi>8.3.</hi>
               </note> made ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock of the Church, (that is, of Gods People congregated together, to worſhip and ſerve God) when hee <note n="(b)" place="margin">Verſe <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> entred into every houſe, and drew out both men and women to put them to Priſon; when he <note n="(c)" place="margin">Act. <hi>9.1.</hi>
               </note> breathed out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the diſciples
<pb facs="tcp:113439:4"/>
of the Lord; when he <note n="(d)" place="margin">Act. <hi>9.2.</hi>
               </note> procured Letters of the High Prieſt to goe to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> where, if he found any of that way (then the hereticall way in his account) he might bring them downe to <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> when he <note n="(e)" place="margin">Act. <hi>8.1.</hi>
               </note> conſented to <hi>Stephens</hi> death: In all theſe violent motions he was zealous and hearty, and thought hee did God good ſervice in the ſuppreſsion of a riſing Sect, that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the High Prieſts, learned Rabbies, and Doctors of the Law, Ceremonies, ſtrict Injunctions, and obſervations of the Judaicall and Prieſtly Law. You ſee how farre miſtaken zeale can goe. Conſider this I beſeech you; I know you are, eſpecially you that are Laymen, zealous as you think for God and his Truth, as <hi>Paul</hi> was: But I hope there will a time come, and I wiſh it were now preſent, when in the midſt of your heat and fervency, the glorious and ſhining brightneſſe of Love will appeare in your hearts like the light ſurrounding <hi>Paul</hi> going to <hi>Damaſcus;</hi> and the ſcales of ignorance and miſtake will fall from your eyes, and then you will lament all the evill, which through weakneſſe you have brought upon your Brethren, you will then blame your owne zeale and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and apply your ſelves more cordially and conſtantly to obſerve our Saviours rule of equity, to doe unto others what you would have others doe unto you.</p>
            <p>Peruſe this Treatiſe I beſeech ye, with a ſingle heart, and unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced mind, and let it ſway you, as the Arguments thereof are efficacious, and the Scriptures therein urged are pertinent and convincing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So wiſheth yours, and all other good Mens true Friend,</hi> H. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113439:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the High and Mighty King James, by the grace of</hi> God, King of great Britain, <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to the Princely and right Honorable Parliament, <hi>Leonard Buſher</hi> wiſheth the wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the zeal of <hi>Joſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and the mercy of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note> with the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of your Spirits in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as your Majeſty and Parliament, do ſtand for the maintenance of the Religion wherein you are born, and for the ſame do moſt zealouſly perſecute with fire &amp; ſword; I have thought it good, and alſo my duty (moſt Royall So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign) to inform your Majeſty and Parliament thereof. In all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility therefore I give you to underſtand, that no Prince or People can poſſible attaine that one true <hi>Religion of the Goſpel,</hi> which is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God by Jeſus Chriſt, meerly by birth,<note n="(a)" place="margin">John. 3.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi> Alſo the Apoſt. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Jam. 1.18</note> 
               <hi>Of his own will be begat us by the word of truth</hi>: and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <p>1 Pet. 1.3.23.</p>
                  <p>Matth. 28. Mark 16.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Being born anew, not of mortall ſeed, but of immortall, by the word of God who liveth and endureth for ever.</hi> Therefore Chriſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this word to be preached to all nations, that thereby they may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the new birth. By which your Majeſty and Parliament may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that the one true <hi>Religion of the Goſpel</hi> is not attained by naturall birth; for then all Princes and peoples, in all nations, ſhould have that one true <hi>Religion of the Goſpel,</hi> the which you ſee and grant, they all have not, yet many of them alſo will defend their Religion (<hi>wherein they are born</hi>)by fire and ſword, as if it were their naturall and earthly inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritances; or had with fire and ſword been gotten, and therefore will with fire and ſword maintain and defend it: But your Majeſty and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament may pleaſe to underſtand, that the Scriptures doe teach, that the one true Religion is gotten by a new birth, even by the word and ſpirit of God, and therewith alſo it is onely maintained and defended, <hi>For the word of God is lively, and mighty in operation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4. Ephe. 6.17. Heb. 4.1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and ſharper then any two edged ſword, and entereth through, even unto the dividing aſunder of the ſoule and the ſpirit, and of the joints, and of the marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and the intents of the heart.</hi> Seeing then the one true Religion of the Goſpel is thus gotten, and thus defended and maintained, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the word preached onely; let it pleaſe your Majeſty and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be intreated to revoke and repeale thoſe <hi>Antichriſtian, Romiſh,</hi> and cruell laws, that force all in our Land, both Prince &amp; people, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113439:5"/>
that Religion wherein the King or Queen were born, or that w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is ſtabliſhed by the Law of man; and in ſtead thereof enact and publiſh that <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19. Mar. 16.16. Acts 8.12. Lu. 24.4, 7. Acts 8.12.37. &amp; <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.41.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtian, gentle and mercifull law of Chriſt,</hi> viz. <hi>Goe teach all Nations, preach the Goſpel to every creature,</hi> that is, Chriſt will have his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to preach and teach the people of all Nations, the things that <hi>concern the Kingdom of God, and the name of Jeſus Meſſiah, repentance and remiſſion of ſins, and to baptize in his name, ſuch as doe beleeve.</hi> And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much alſo that the falſe and Antichriſtian religion did come <hi>by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of error and doctrine of devils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1. Rev. 16.14.</note> and not by fire and ſword: therefore by the ſpirit of Chriſt, and doctrine of the word of God, muſt it be driven out of the hearts and conſciences, both of Prince and People, and not by fire and ſword, as the falſe Biſhops and Miniſters have and doe ſtill perſwade. Therefore may it pleaſe your Majeſty and Parliament, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that (by fire and ſword) to conſtrain Princes and peoples, to receive that one true <hi>Religion of the Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 9 38, 39.</note> is wholly againſt the minde and mercifull Law of Chriſt, dangerous both to King &amp; State, a means to decreaſe the Kingdom of Chriſt: and a means to increaſe the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Antichriſt, as theſe reaſons following do manifeſt; The which I humbly beſeech your Majeſty and Parliament carefully to conſider, and that according to the Word of God, which ſhall <hi>judge every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deeds</hi>:<note place="margin">
                  <p>Mat. 16.27. Rev. 16.14. Luke 9.55, 56.</p>
                  <p>Joh. 12.47.</p>
               </note> &amp; perſecution is a work well pleaſing to all falſ Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Biſhops, but it is contrary to the mind of Chriſt, <hi>who came not to judge and deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> And though ſome men and women beleeve not at the firſt houre, yet may they at the <note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 20.6, 7.</note> eleventh houre, if they be not perſecuted to death before: And no King nor Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops can, or is able to command faith, <note n="(e)" place="margin">Eph. 2 8 1 Tim. 1.13. Act. 20.11.</note> 
               <hi>That is the gift of God, who worketh in us both the will and the deed of his own good pleaſure</hi>: ſet him not a day therefore, in which, if his creature hear not and beleeve not, you will impriſon and burn him. <hi>Paul</hi> was a blaſphemer, and alſo a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter, and could not be converted by the Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Chriſt, yet at laſt was received to mercy, and converted extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily by Chriſt himſelf,<note place="margin">Jam. 5 11. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 3.9. 2 Cor. 5.19.</note> who is <hi>very pitifull and mercifull, and would have no man to periſh, but would that all men come to repentance,</hi> but not by perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, but by <hi>the word of reconciliation which he hath committed to his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi>: And as Kings and Biſhops cannot command the wind, ſo they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not command faith,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and as the winde bloweth where it liſteth, ſo is every man that is born of the ſpirit.</hi> You may force men to Church againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> but they will beleev as they did afore, when they com there, for God giveth a bleſſing onely to his own ordinance, and abhorreth Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113439:5"/>
And Kings are to think that they are men as well as Kings,<note place="margin">Act. 9.15. 1 Tim. 2.1.2. 1. Cor. 7.2.22. Wiſe 6.1.8.</note> and that Chriſt hath ordained that ſame meanes of faith for Kings which he hath for ſubjects, and that ſubjects are <hi>Chriſts freemen, as well as Kings ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and Kings that beleeve are Chriſts Servants,</hi> even as ſubjects are Kings ſervants, and both are bought with a price, <hi>therefore both ought not to bee the ſervants of men in matter of faith and religion</hi>: but Kings ſhall give a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter account at the day of judgment, then their ſubjects: &amp; to judge men now for religion, is to judge afore the time, &amp; alſo to ſit in the judgment ſeat of Chriſt, to whom onely it belongeth, yet not before the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, how much leſſe to Kings and Biſhops?<note place="margin">Rom. 2.16. Act. 10.42.</note> I read that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor (called the great) wrote to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he would not force &amp; conſtraine any man to the faith, but onely admoniſh &amp; commit the judgment to God. Chriſts kingdom is not of this world,<note place="margin">Ioh. 18 36.10.17.</note> therefore may it not be purchaſed, nor defended with the weapons of this world, but by his word and ſpirit: no other weapons hath he given to his Church which is his ſpirituall kingdom. Therefore Chriſt ſaith:<note place="margin">Mat. 18.17</note> 
               <hi>He that wil not heare the church, let him he to thee as a heathen and a publicane:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.10.17.</note> he ſaith not burne, baniſh or impriſon him, that is Antichriſts ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. And though a man be an heretick, yet ought he not to be burnt, but to be rejected, <hi>after once or twice admonition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.10.</note> that is caſt out of the Church, but as in the church of <hi>Rome</hi> people of all ſorts are by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion forced there into by the Biſhops &amp; Miniſters thereof, ſo it is in the Church of <hi>England</hi> alſo, which ſheweth that the Biſhops &amp; Miniſters of <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; <hi>England</hi> are of one ſpirit, in gathering people to their faith and church, which is the ſpirit of <hi>Satan,</hi> who knoweth welth at his kingdom (the falſe Church) would greatly decay, if perſecution were laid down: ſeeing himſelf cannot ſtand before the word and ſpirit of God, much leſſe his Biſhops &amp; Miniſters: therefore he wil have them, for a name and ſhew, to uſe the word of God, but indeed, if the falſe interpretation and alledging of the Scriptures wil not help, then (ſaith he) conſtrain them with fire and ſword: or elſe (if people have libertie of conſcience) they will try the ſpirits, which of them is of God, as the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: and then ſaith he, the Prince as well as people will try all things,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>and keepe that which is good, and wil alſo prove themſelves</hi> (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth) <hi>whether they are in the Apoſtolike faith or not</hi>:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5</note> &amp; as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> provoketh the Magiſtrates to perſecute to death, ſuch as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated out of her, ſo doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> provoke the Magiſtrats to perſecute to death ſuch as ſhe excommunicates: And as the Biſhops and Miniſters of <hi>Rome</hi> will perſwade the prince and people, to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113439:6"/>
heare and read none but themſelves, ſo do the Biſhops and Miniſters of of <hi>England</hi> alſo: but the Biſhops and Miniſters of the Apoſtolick church doe perſwade all men, <hi>to prove and try the Spirits whether they are of God, which they cannot doe,</hi> except they heare and read other mens doctrines as well as the Biſhops and their Miniſters; neither can they if they would, ſo long as the Biſhops have power from the King and State to ſilence and impriſon, &amp;c. all Preachers, and to burne all books which teach not their doctrines. Your Majeſty and Parliament ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that all thoſe that confeſſe freely without compulſion, that <hi>Ieſus is the Meſſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 5.1. &amp; 1 Joh. 4.2 1 Cor. 12.13</note> 
               <hi>the Lord, and that he came in fleſh, are to be eſteemed the children of God and true chriſtians, ſeeing ſuch are born of God</hi>; and no man can ſay, that Jeſus is the Lord but by the holy Ghoſt, therefore not to be perſecuted.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Abel</hi> killed not <hi>Cain,</hi> but was killed himſelf; and as <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> did not perſecute <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> but was perſecuted of <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> (who,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.29.</note> and <hi>Cain</hi> were figures of all perſecuters) ſo the beleeving doe not perſecute the unbeleeving, nor the true Church the falſ, but the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving and true Church are (as they have been) moſt often perſecuted themſelves, of whom <hi>Abel, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were figures, whoſe children are all beleevers and freemen, that ſtand faſt in <hi>the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made them free,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>and will not be tangled with the yoke of bondage,</hi> no not with circumciſion, much leſſe with the diſcipline and doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Biſhops are able Miniſters of the fire and ſword, both to Prince and people, as many Hiſtories doe lamentably witnes, to their utter infamy and overthrow: alſo, if the beleeving ſhould perſecute the unbeleeving to death, who ſhould remaine alive? then none but the beleeving ſhould live in the world, and the unbeleeving ſhould dye in their unbelief, and ſo periſh for ever: the Lord will not that the beleeving ſhould live to the deſtruction of the unbeleeving, but unto their converſion, edification, and ſalvation: And by perſecuting of Prince and people to death, becauſe they will not heare and beleeve, is no gaining of ſouls unto God, but unto the devill. And whereas igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and wicked Biſhops may think to win ſouls by killing Prince and people for Religion, they are deceived greatly, for thereby they loſe many ſouls, <hi>viz.</hi> their own and the unbeleeving, their own they loſe, becauſe they wilfully break the Lords Commandement, that ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.20.</note> meaning ſuch as are not corporall malefactors; and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which dye in their unbeleef, they confeſſe themſelves are eternally loſt, except they (as ſome of their miniſters) hold a redemption after this life. And the Biſhops ſhould know that error and hereſie cannot
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113439:6"/>
be killed by the fire and ſword, but by the word and ſpirit of God, that is the onely weapons of Chriſts Biſhops and Miniſters, and ſuch only Chriſts miniſters do uſe, whoſe lives and converſations are ſo harmles, holy and gentle, that thereby, and by their deaths and ſufferings they win many ſouls unto God; whereby they are known from all falſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and miniſters, who like wolves and beares, (not like ſheepe and lambs) make prey and devour both Prince and people that are not of their kind, if they be able to maſter them.</p>
            <p>Beſides, may it pleaſe your Majeſty and Parliament to underſtand, that the beleeving man that hath an unbeleeving wife,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.16</note> and the beleeving woman that hath an unbeleeving husband, cannot live together, as the Scripture teaches, for the ſalvation of the unbeleeving, if they be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted to death; indeed ſome thereby are forced to confeſſe with the mouth that which they beleeve not in heart, and ſo are made true diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, in ſtead of true Chiſtians, wherby many men and women are deceived with diſſembling husbands and wives, as well as the King and State are deceived with diſſembling ſervants and ſubjects; but the word of God (if permiſſion of conſcience might be granted) would procure upright, pure, and unfained husbands and wives, ſervants and ſubjects, ſo that thereby neither Prince nor people ſhould be deceived; for all good ſhepherds wil divide and ſeparate, &amp; not force, ſlay, and perſecute, for if men and women be found Hereticks, they ſhall be ſeparated from the Church, but if they be unbeleevers, they ſhall not be joyned unto it, untill they be converted by the word of God, much leſſe forced: which converſion for ought we know, may be at their death, if not afore, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord calleth ſome at the eleventh houre, ſo well as at the firſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 20. 6, 7</note> and not at the King and Biſhops pleaſures. Kings and Magiſtrates are to rule temporall affaires by the ſwords of their temporall kingdoms: and Biſhops and Miniſters are to rule ſpirituall affaires by the word and ſpirit of God; the ſword of Chriſts ſpirituall kingdom, and not to intermeddle one with anothers authority, office, and function: and it is a great ſhame for the Biſhops and Miniſters not to be able to rule in their Church, without the aſſiſtance of the King and Magiſtrate, yea, it is a great ſign they are none of Chriſts Biſhops and Miniſters, if they were, they would not be afraid nor aſhamed of their faith, nor yet would they perſwade Princes and people to perſecute and force one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to beleeve them, but would uſe only the aſſiſtance of Gods word and ſpirit; and therewith ſuffer their faith and doctrine to be examined, proved, and diſputed both by word and writing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113439:7"/>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.7.9.11.</note>And he is a true Biſhop who is unreprovable, and that is able to ſtop the mouths of his adverſaries, by Gods word and Spirit onely, &amp; whoſe faith and diſcipline agree with the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and maketh no contradiction; but all thoſe Biſhops that force Princes and peoples to receive their faith and diſcipline by perſecution, doe (with <hi>Iudas</hi>) goe againſt Chriſt in his members with ſwords, ſtaves, and halberds, who ſeeing Gods word will not help them, betake themſelves with all haſte and hazard unto the authority of the King and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>I read that a Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> would have conſtrained a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror to the Chriſtian faith, unto whom the Emperor anſwered, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that Christ was an excellent Prophet, but he did never (ſo far as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand) command that men ſhould with the power of weapons bee conſtrained to beleeve his law; and verily, I alſo do force no man to beleeve Mahomets law.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I read that <hi>Iews, Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> are tolerated in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and yet are peaceable, though ſo contrary the one to the other. If this he ſo, how much more ought Chriſtians not to force one another to Religion? <hi>and how much more ought Chriſtians to tolerate Chriſtians, when as the</hi> Turks <hi>do tolerate them? ſhall we be leſſe mercifull then the</hi> Turks? <hi>or ſhall we learne the</hi> Turks <hi>to perſecute Chriſtians? It is not onely unmercifull, but unnaturall and abominable, yea, monſtrous for one Chriſtian to vex and deſtroy another for difference and queſtions of Religion, and though tares have overgrown the wheate, yet Chriſt will have them let alone till harveſt</hi>;<note place="margin">Mat. 13.29.30, 38.</note> 
               <hi>leſt while you goe about to pluck up the tares, you pluck up alſo the wheat with them,</hi> as your predeceſſors have done, who thought they had gathered up the tares and burned them; but you ſee now that they have burned the wheat in ſtead of tares. Wherfore in all humility and Chriſtian modeſty I doe affirm, that through the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full weed-hook of perſecution (which your predeceſſors have uſed, and by your Majeſty and Parliament is ſtil continued) there is ſuch a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of wheat plucked up, and ſuch a multitude of tares left behinde, that the wheat which remain cannot yet appeare in any right viſible congregation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Acts 3.17.</note>And now beloved Soveraign and Parliament, I know that through ignorance you doe perſecute, as did alſo your predeceſſors, <hi>Amend your lives therefore and turne, that your ſinnes may be put away when the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord; who before hath ſhewed by the month of his holy ſervant</hi> John,<note place="margin">Rev. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>that the woman</hi> (meaning the Church) <hi>ſhould fly into the wilderneſſe for a time, times, and half a time, from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113439:7"/>
and perſecution of the ſerpent. And that the winepreſſe ſhould bee troden without the City, untill bloud came out of the winepreſſe, unto the horſe bridles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 14.20.</note> 
               <hi>by the ſpace of a thouſand and ſix hundred furlongs: and thus he hath fulfilled it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore I humbly beſeech you, ſuffer not your Biſhops and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters any longer to perſwade, to force your ſubjects or any others, to their faith and Church by perſecution, neither ſuffer them therewith to defend their faith and Church againſt their adverſaries: if they have not any thing from Gods word againſt us, let them yeeld and ſubmit themſelves; if they think they have any thing againſt us, let them betake themſelves onely to Gods word, both in word and writing,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16</note> 
               <hi>For the whole Scripture is given by inſpiration of God to that purpoſe, and is profitable to teach, to reprove, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be abſolute, being made perfect unto all good works</hi>: with which ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (and not with fire and ſword) your Majeſties Biſhops and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ought to be armed and weaponed:<note place="margin">
                  <p>Mat. 10.14, 15.</p>
                  <p>Mat. 16.11.</p>
               </note> and whoſoever ſhall not heare the words of ſuch Biſhops and Miniſters; then ſuch Biſhops &amp; Miniſters are commanded by Chriſt (not to impriſon, burn, baniſh, &amp; hang them) but to <hi>ſhake the duſt of their feet againſt them, for a witneſſe when they depart from them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.51.</note> 
               <hi>affirming that at the day of judgment it ſhall be eaſier for Sodome and Gomorrah, then for ſuch perſons: and this commandement of Chriſt,</hi> did his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters obey as you may read. By which, and by that which follow, your gracious Ma<hi rend="sup">ty</hi>., and Princely and honorable Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament may perceive the will and mind of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt, unto whoſe mercy I commend you, and to the word and wiſdom of his grace, which is able to build further, and to give you an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all them which are ſanctified, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithfull and loving ſubject Leonard Buſher</hi>: not <hi>Furbuſher.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">There is one <hi>Furbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher</hi> a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in this Land.</note>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>Certain Reaſons againſt Perſecution.</head>
            <p>FIrſt, becauſe Chriſt hath not commanded any King, Biſhop, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to perſecute the people, for difference and judgement in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Religion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe Chriſt hath commanded his Biſhops and Miniſters to perſwade Prince and people to heare and beleeve the Goſpel, by his word and ſpirit, and (as Ambaſſadors for him) to beſeech both Prince
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113439:8"/>
and people to be reconciled unto God,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.20</note> and not (as Tyrants) to force and conſtraine them by perſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">At <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors &amp; Martyrs of Chriſt hath Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bee ſlaine ſince Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended. Mark 13.9. Perſecution deſtroys Chriſtians but not er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</note>Thirdly, becauſe through perſecution it will come to paſſe that the Ambaſſadors of the onely <hi>ſpirituall Lord and King Ieſus,</hi> may he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and impriſoned, burned, hanged, or baniſhed for delivering the meſſage of their gracious Lord, ſincerely and often, both to Prince and people; which to doe, is a more hainous fact then to perſecute the Ambaſſadors of the greateſt King and Prince in the world: for in ſtead of hereticks, they ſhall (as they have already) burn, baniſh, and hang the Ambaſſadors of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; who doth chooſe out whom he pleaſeth, to beare his name <hi>before Kings and Rulers, for a testimoniall to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe then we cannot ſay, <hi>we have the liberty of the Goſpel in our Land,</hi> ſeeing where that is, there is no perſecution for any difference in Religion, nor forcing of the conſcience to beleeve the Goſpel, except by the word and ſpirit of God onely, the which do wound and kill the errors of men, and not their perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>2 Cor. 10.4 1 Tim. 1.13, 15.</p>
                  <p>Luke 9.53.55.</p>
                  <p>Perſecutors rebuked of Chriſt.</p>
               </note>Fifthly, becauſe <hi>Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners,</hi> and not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, though they be blaſphemers, ſeeing the Lord may convert them as he did <hi>Saul</hi> (after called <hi>Paul</hi>) and though they have difference in Religion, or will not heare nor beleeve in Chriſt, that they may be converted, yet ought you not to perſecute them, ſeeing Chriſt rebuketh ſuch, &amp; his Father ſent him not into the world, to condemn the world, but to ſave it: be ye followers therefore of Chriſt, and not of Antichriſt, in gathering people to the faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>1 Cor. 10, 32.</p>
                  <p>Col. 4.5.</p>
               </note>Sixthly, becauſe then <hi>you ſhall not walke wiſely towards them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> as the Scripture teacheth, <hi>but ſhall offend alſo the Iewes, and all other ſtrangers who account it tyranny,</hi> to have their conſciences forced to <hi>religion</hi> by perſecution.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, becauſe if perſecution bee not laid downe, and liberty of conſcience ſet up, then cannot the Jews, nor any ſtrangers, nor others contrary minded be ever converted in our Land; for ſo long as they know aforehand, that they ſhall be forced to beleeve againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, they will never ſeek to inhabit there: by which means you keep them from the Apoſtolique faith, if the apoſtolique faith be only taught where perſecution is.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, becauſe if freedom of conſcience be not ſet up, and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113439:8"/>
laid down, then all the Kings ſubjects, and all ſtrangers inhabiting the Land (that ſhall beleeve the Apoſtolique faith) muſt depart the land to ſome free country, or elſe abide the danger of burning, baniſhing,<note place="margin">Perſecution does make many ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> hanging and impriſoning: the firſt will be a great impoveriſhing and weakning of our land, beſides a loſſe of the faith fulleſt ſubjects and friends. The ſecond will provoke the Lord to wrath, by ſpilling the blood of his faithfull ſervants, ambaſſadors, and witneſſes, and alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the mouths of all ſtrangers, to ſpeake yet more lamentably of the cruel and bloody perſecution of our Land.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, becauſe if perſecution continue, then the King and State ſhall have (againſt their wils) many diſſemblers in authority and office, both in Court, City, and Country: yea, no man of any degree ſhall know whether they are all faithfull and true Chriſtians that are about him, and with whom he hath to doe: ſeeing moſt men will conforme themſelves for feare of perſecution, although in their hearts they hate and deteſt the Religion whereto they are forced by law, the which is very dangerous and hurtfull both to King and State in time of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from beyond the ſeas, and in rebellion at home; for they that are not faithfull to God in their Religion, will never be faithfull to the King and State in their allegiance; ſpecially being tryed by a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or by a mighty rebell: but wil (to encreaſe their honors &amp; reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues) conform themſelves; and ſome to ſave their honors, land, goods and lives, will yeeld and ſubmit, though againſt their wils, even as they have done in caſe of Religion; for through forcing men to Church by perſecution, the true hearted ſubjects are forced out of the Land, and out of the world, ſome baniſhed, others burn'd, hang'd and impriſoned to death.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, becauſe then,<note place="margin">Perſecution cauſes many religions in the Church.</note> if there be many religions in the land (as it is well known there are) it will come to paſſe (through the continuance of perſecution) that many religions will be continued in the Church, ſeeing all are forced to Church, who bring their Religions with them as well as their bodies, whereby all their devotion is againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and all the Church is a confuſed <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18.2.4</note> 
               <hi>full of every uncleane and hatefull bird, even a bold of foule Spirits,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaketh; <hi>out of which the people of God are commanded to flee, leſt (as of their ſins) they be alſo partakers of their plague.</hi> And the Biſhops (the authors of perſecution) are very ignorant to think that when they have gotten people to their Church by perſecution, that then they have gotten them to their faith
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113439:9"/>
and Religion,<note place="margin">Better were it to have many religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the land, then in the Church.</note> the which is nothing ſo, for moſt people (though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minded) to ſave life and goods, will diſſemble their Religion; as for example the Jews in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> and the Papiſts, Reformiſts and others in <hi>England</hi>; but when they come hither or to ſome other free City or Counrry (where praiſed be God is liberty of the Goſpel) then they ſhew that before they diſſembled, to avoid the cruell perſecution of our Land.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Biſhops bewray great ignorance, when they perſwade the King and Parliament, to force Prince and people to Church by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution: for if that be the means to come to the Church of Chriſt; then Chriſt hath taught us to flee the means of ſalvation, ſeeing hee hath taught us to flee perſecution:<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.23. Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to flee perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, <hi>ergo</hi> it cannot poſſible be good Mat 7. 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> ſee 2 Tim. 3.3, 4.</p>
               </note> the which the Biſhops and their Miniſters perſwade to be a great means to bring men to the Church: Indeed I confeſſe it is the onely meanes to bring Prince and people to the falſe church; and therfore Chriſt teacheth us to flee that means leaſt through perſecution (which is a great temptation) we be conſtrained to <hi>goe the broad way</hi> (which is the falſe Church) <hi>that leadeth to deſtruction, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny go in thereat</hi>: and no marvail, for there men may bee any thing, except good Chriſtians: for (beſides <hi>Demos</hi> the worldling, and <hi>Hymeneus</hi> the blaſphemer, and many other ſorts of indifferent Chriſtians, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants, covetous, and profane perſons) there are notable Rebels and Traytors; yea moſt cruell and deſperate <hi>Traytors and Rebels,</hi> as <hi>Digby, Catesby, Piercy, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe unread and unheard treachery will never be forgotten; which perſons, if they had not bin forced to Church againſt their conſciences, had never enterprized ſuch horrible and hatefull trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>And the Biſhops ſhould underſtand that it is preaching and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting that getteth people to the Church of Chriſt; for the Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>Faith is by hearing, and bearing by the word of God,</hi> and not by the ſword of Princes and Magiſtrates, as they perſwade and practice. And therefore the Biſhops of our land are truly called <hi>Antichriſts:</hi> for by their beaſtly and bloody perſecution, as well as by their blaſphemous titles, erroneous doctrines, and popiſh government, may they juſtly be termed <hi>Antichriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 2 Theſ. 2. &amp; 1 Tim. 4. 2 Pet. 2.</note>Eleventhly, becauſe Chriſt foretold, <hi>That many falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe, and deceive many; yea, if it were poſſible, the very elect</hi>: and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did prophecy a departure from the faith: And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>There ſhould be falſe teachers now among the people</hi>: And <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113439:9"/>
Kings ſhould give their power and authority unto the beaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 57.13, 17</note> 
               <hi>untill the words of God be fulfilled</hi>; therefore if perſecution be not laid downe, and liberty of the Goſpel ſet up, you may perſecute the true Chriſtians in ſtead of the falſe, as your predeceſſors have done; for they are now (like as they were then) the ſmalleſt number: and the falſe Chriſtians are now (like as they were then) the greateſt number: and perſecution is a notable mark of the falſe Church and her Biſhops and miniſters:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.3, 4. &amp; 5.11. &amp; 6.12.</note> and therefore <hi>Christ would have us flee from it,</hi> who overcame the devill and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by the word of God, and by a good, meek and gentle life, whoſe ſteps his Biſhops and Miniſters ought to follow.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, becauſe perſecution of ſuch as do preach and teach Chriſt is a great hinderance to the liberty of the Goſpel:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> Falſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops reach Turkes and Pagans to perſecute Chriſtians.</note> 
               <hi>For thereby are the Iews, Turks, and Pagans occaſioned and encouraged to perſecute like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all ſuch as preach and teach Chriſt in their Dominions.</hi> For if chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings and Magiſtrates will not ſuffer Chriſtians to preach, and preach the Goſpel of Chriſt freely and peaceably in their Dominions, how ſhould you expect it of the infidells, unto whom Biſhops and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings and Magiſtrates ought to give a good example, and not an evill, as to burn, baniſh, hang and Impriſon peaceable and godly chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that are no traytors, nor theeves, nor fighters, nor manſlayers, nor yet ſwearers, nor drunkards, nor whoremaſters, nor ſuch like. And the King and Parliament may pleaſe to permit all ſorts of Chriſtians, yea, Jews, Turks, and Pagans, ſo long as they are peaceable, and no malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, as is above-mentioned: which if they be found to be under two or three witneſſes, let them be puniſhed according to Gods word: alſo if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be found to be willing lyers, falſe accuſers, falſe alledgers and quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Scriptures, or other mens writings (as ſome men willingly do) let them be puniſhed according to right and juſtice, it is due deſert &amp; no perſecution, but let Gods word have his ful and free paſſage among them all, even to the end of their lives, in all bountifulneſs, long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and patience, knowing that it is ordained of Gods rich mercy, to lead the infidels, and ſuch as erre unto repentance and amendment,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4. 2 Tit. 2.25.</note> out of the ſnare of the devil, of whom they are taken and deceived.</p>
            <p>Thirteenthly, becauſe perſecution for Religion is to force the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to force and conſtrain men and womens conſciences to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion againſt their wils, is to tyranize over the ſoul as well as over the body, and herein the Biſhops commit a greater ſin, then if they force the bodies of women and maids againſt their wills: yea,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.2</note> herein they are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113439:10"/>
more cruell and greater tyrants then the Turks,<note place="margin">Falſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops worſe then Turks and Pagans.</note> who though they force the bodies of ſtrangers to ſlavery and bondage, yet they let the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence go free, yea to Chriſtians that are ſo contrary to them in Religions but theſe Idol-biſhops will force the conſciences of Chriſtians, their own naturall Countrymen,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Falſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
                  <p>2 Theſſ. 2.4 1 Cor 6.19, 20. and 2 Cor. 6.16, 17. with Rev. 18.4. &amp; 2 Pet. 2.1. 1 Pet. 1.19</p>
               </note> even unto ſpirituall bondage and ſlavery; and herein they <hi>commit fornication both with Prince and people, and have made all, both ſmall and great, to receive a mark in their right hand, or in their foreheads, ſo that no man may buy or ſell, ſave he that will goe to Church,</hi> and ſubmit to the Biſhops ordinances, and name and mark of their beaſtly and bloody perſecution, through which as God, they ſit in, and reigne over the conſciences both of Prince and people, which is the ſpirituall ſeat and temple of God bought at a dear price, even with the precious blood of their onely ſpirituall Lord Jeſus <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the true Shepheard and biſhop of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>And the Biſhops in forcing men and womens conſciences, doe therein play the Antichriſt ſo well as the Popes: and indeed there is never a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in the land but is a Pope, for Pope in latin is <hi>Papa,</hi> and <hi>Papa</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Father in Engliſh, all the Biſhops in our land are called reverend Fathers; therefore all the Biſhops in our land are called reverend Popes, ſo many Lord Biſhops, ſo many reverend Fathers, ſo many reverend Popes:<note place="margin">If Idolaters ought to be ſlain, then ought all thoſe that ſubmit and yeeld ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and reverence unto theſe Biſhops to be ſlain, who then ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in land alive? Rev. 17.13.</note> and theſe are all ſo many Antichriſts, ſo many Idols, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falſe Gods of <hi>England</hi>: how many are thy Gods whom thou doſt ſerve? For whoſe ſpirituall adoration, the knee of every man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muſt bow, or elſe they ſhall be perſecuted: unto whom the King ought not any longer to give his authority and power, leſt hee fulfill the Scripture, which ſaith, that Kings ſhould give their power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority unto the beaſt.</p>
            <p>Fourteenthly, becauſe the burning, baniſhing, hanging, and impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of men and women, by Proteſtants, for difference of Religion, do juſtifie the burning, baniſhing and impriſoning of men and women, by the Papiſts, for difference of religion, even as the Papiſts doe juſtifie the Turks and Pagans in ſuch like cruelty and tyranny; wherein now is the Proteſtants more mercifull then the Papiſts, or the Papiſts then the Turks? <hi>Therefore as the Papiſts (when they complain of the Turks and Pagans, for their bloody perſecution) doe therein condemn themſelves, becauſe they are found to do the ſame, yea worſe, for it is greater tyranny for one Chriſtian to force &amp; kil another, then for Turks and Pagans to kil a chriſtian, for that is no ſuch great wonder, ſeeing it is a paganiſh part, who have no better knowledge, but Chriſtians ſhould have better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113439:10"/>
and more mercy then to play the pagans againſt chriſtians</hi>:<note place="margin">Note.</note> So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Proteſtants, when they complain of the Papiſts for their bloody and beaſtly perſecution, doe therein condemn themſelves, ſeeing they doe the ſame, for which they blame others, and ſo are rebuked of the Scripture, which ſaith, <hi>Therefore thou are inexcuſable O thou man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 2.1.3.</note> 
               <hi>whoſoever thou art that blameſt another, for in that thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt doest the ſame things: and thinkeſt thou this O thou man (that judgeſt them which do ſuch things, and thou doeſt the ſame) that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment of God</hi>?</p>
            <p>Fifteenthly, becauſe his Majeſty and Parliament would not willingly themſelves be forc'd againſt their conſciences, by the perſecution of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and his Princes: ſo I beſeech them (according to the law Chriſt hath injoyned Chriſtians) not by perſecution to force other mens conſciences againſt their wills by the irritation of the Biſhops of our land.<note place="margin">Luk. 6 31. Or provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Sixteenthly, becauſe perſecution do cauſe men and women to make ſhipwrack of faith and good conſciences, by forcing a Religion upon them, even againſt their minds and conſciences, and alſo do ſend them quick to the devill in their errors, if that be hereſie for which they are hanged and burned; which to do, is a moſt unchriſtian, unnaturall,<note place="margin">
                  <p>King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> was an enemy to perſecution <hi>Act.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mon.</hi> pag. 1484. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian anſwer of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rev. 16.14.</p>
               </note> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and tyrannous deed; and I am ſure you would not be content to be ſo dealt withall your ſelves: but indeed the Popiſh and Idol-biſhops are the authors hereof againſt the people, as well as of other perſecution againſt the Princes. For antichriſtian Biſhops do draw Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hereto againſt their mind, as may appear by <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, that godly King of famous memory, who being urged by his bloody Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to ſubſcribe to the burning of a woman called <hi>Joane Butcher,</hi> hee anſwered, <hi>will you have me to ſend her quick to the devill in her error</hi>? But when his blood-thirſty Biſhops would have no nay, he ſaid againe to Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> I lay all the charge thereof on you before God; and <hi>Cranmer</hi> ſaid, he had never ſo much to do in all his life as to procure it: whereby I doe perceive that godly Kings are drawn to Battail againſt the Saints, by antichriſtian Biſhops and falſe Prophets, who otherwiſe would rule and reigne more agreeable to the mind of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Alſo, hereby may all men perceive that the Councell and Biſhops could not ſatisfie the Kings conſcience by their perſwaſion, if they could have ſhewed him the word of God for burning that Chriſtian, it would have prevailed with that godly King, and he might then of faith have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113439:11"/>
conſented, but his anſwer ſhoweth that he was not of their mind, for all that they had ſaid, and therfore now, if it pleaſe you to require of your Biſhops, warrant from the word of God for the perſecuting of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or for forcing Prince and people to Church, you ſhall finde not one Biſhop, yea not all of them together, though aſſiſted with their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, will be able to ſhew warrant from Gods word, whereby to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your conſciences thereunto:<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23</note> and whatſoever is not of faith is ſin, and whatſoever is not from Gods word, cannot be of faith.</p>
            <p>Seventeenthly, becauſe perſecution of Chriſtians by Chriſtians doe not onely juſtifie Papiſts, and teach the Jewes and Pagans to perſecute Chriſtians; but alſo do teach the Papiſts and others (that know not the mind of Chriſt, and once get the upperhand) to perſecute thoſe that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>By Digby, Catesby,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 11.29 Luk. 14 27.</note> yea, it is a means (as we have had lamentable experience) to ſet (ſuch as are forced to Church againſt their conſciences) at deadly hatred againſt the King and State, and urgeth all them to treaſon and rebellion, that have not truly learned Chriſt, who himſelf was perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to death, whoſe harmles croſſe all true Chriſtians muſt take up, and whoſe gentle and humble ſteps they muſt follow and walk in, or elſe they cannot be his diſciples, nor ſheep of his paſture. And neither can the Papiſts be perſwaded that perſecution is a ſin, ſo long as they and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtians are alſo perſecuted by the proteſtants: ſeeing the Papiſts do build their perſecution on the ſame ground with the proteſtants: but both ſorts of Biſhops doe erre groſly, as ſhall be ſhewed (God willing) when they make their defence, except herewith their conſciences bee convinced to yeeld, as I wiſh they may for the ſalvation of their owne ſouls, the peace both of Prince and people, and the ſafety of the King and State. In the mean while it is to be obſerved, that thoſe Biſhops, and Miniſters which perſwade the King and Parliament, to burn, baniſh, hang and impriſon, for difference of Religion, are blood-ſuckers and manſlayers, and ſuch (it cannot be denyed) cauſed Kings &amp; Magiſtrates, to be their executioners and tormentors, in burning the Martyrs in former times, even in the days of King <hi>Henry the eight, and Qu. Mary,</hi> as the books of <hi>Acts and Monuments</hi> will witneſſe if they bee not burned; and I ask the Biſhops and their Miniſters,<note place="margin">Act 4.19.</note> if the <hi>martyrs</hi> ſhould have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the King and Queen, rather then have ſuffered death.</p>
            <p>And now I muſt humbly, and with all reverence do beſeech his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and Parliament, adviſedly to conſider among themſelves, whether the Prince or Princeſſe (differing with the Church now in matter of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113439:11"/>
conſcience and religion,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The Bps. as the High prieſts, force men to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey man ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then God.</p>
                  <p>Note well.</p>
               </note> ſtabliſhed by law in our land (as the right no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth did in Qu. Maries dayes</hi>) do not incur the danger and cruelty of the law now, as that worthy Princeſſe did then, ſeeing that popiſh and cruell law ſtandeth ſtill in force in moſt points of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? and who dare truſt the Biſhops and their adherents in ſuch a caſe, the matter lying in their hands?</p>
            <p>Let it be ſuppoſed that the Princes heart ſhould be moved by the Lord to embrace the <hi>Apoſtolick faith and diſcipline,</hi> ſhall he be forced to beleeve as the Biſhops do, againſt his conſcience, ſhall he be conſtrained to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to their government and diſcipline againſt his conſcience? ſhall hee live in vexation and perſecution, and in danger of his life by the Biſhops and law ſtabliſhed, as the Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did? yea, it muſt be thus with our right noble Prince, except there be partiality, yea it wil be thus with his princely perſon, except thoſe popiſh and cruell laws be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>Wherfore I meekly intreat, ſeeing death is moſt certain,<note place="margin">Better to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, then tarry till to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrow.</note> though moſt uncertain when, that thoſe antichriſtian and popiſh laws may bee diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled and made void in time, leſt wee all lament and bewaile it, when it wil be too late. And I pray your Majeſty and Honors to conſider,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.16 Gen. 17.6. Rom. 4 17.</note> 
               <hi>that Kings and Princes hearts are in the hands of the Lord (as the rivers of waters) to turn as he will</hi>: &amp; the Scripture ſaith, <hi>the ten horns (by which I underſtand ten Kings) ſhall hate the whore and make her deſolate and naked.</hi> Likewiſe the Scripture ſaith to <hi>Abraham</hi> (the father of beleeving Princes as well as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving people) <hi>Alſo I will make thee exceeding fruitfull, and will make na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thee: yea, Kings ſhall proceed of thee</hi>: which Scripture doe alſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the judgment of thoſe men that hold a Chriſtian may not bee a King nor Magiſtrate:<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſmael,</hi> and <hi>Edom</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.8. with <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13.18. &amp; 16.10. &amp; 17.18.20. &amp; 26.3. &amp; 21.13.</p>
                  <p>Gen. 14. 14.</p>
               </note> Let ſuch conſider that the Lord here ſpeaketh of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpirituall ſeed, and not of his naturall ſeed; becauſe if it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of his naturall ſeed, then cannot <hi>Abraham</hi> be the father of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nations, ſeeing all <hi>Abrahams</hi> naturall ſeed are called Jews, and are but one nation of the Iews; ſo that the covenant of <hi>God</hi> could not be perfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med that ſaid, <hi>I wil make nations of thee, yea Kings ſhal proceed of thee</hi>: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be underſtood of his ſpirituall ſeed, of which may be Kings and Princes that are not naturally deſcended of him, as well as people that are naturally deſcended of him; therefore beleeving Kings may ſafely walk in the ſteps of their father <hi>Abraham,</hi> and with their ſwords defend their ſubjects againſt their adverſaries, and redeem their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren out of the jaws of all devouring beaſts and bloody perſecutors,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> for they beare not the ſword for nought.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113439:12"/>And now alſo I deſire thoſe ſubjects (of what degree ſoever, that would deſtroy their Kings and Governours for difference in religion) to conſider, that therin they juſtifie their Kings and Governours, which deſtroy their ſubjects for difference of Religion: for as it is ſin for Kings and Governours to deſtroy their ſubjects for difference of Religion, at the perſwaſion of their Biſhops; ſo is it ſin (but in a higher degree) for ſubjects to deſtroy their Kings and Governors for difference of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the perſwaſion of their Biſhops and Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Therfore perſecution for difference in religion is a monſtrous &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell beaſt, that deſtroyeth both Prince and people, hindereth the Goſpel of Chriſt, and ſcattereth his diſciples that witnes and profeſſe his name.</p>
            <p>But permiſſion of conſcience in difference of Religion, ſaveth both Prince and people, for it is a meek and gentle lambe, which not onely furthereth and advanceth the goſpel, but alſo foſtereth and cheriſheth thoſe that profeſſe it, as may be ſeen by the permiſſion of the Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and others that were permitted and foſtered in <hi>Dutchland</hi> at that time.<note place="margin">Permiſſion of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to the goſpel and a ſafety both to prince and people.</note> Alſo permiſſion of conſcience is a great and ſure band and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to the King and State, as may likewiſe be ſeen in the ſame Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who if ſhe had not been permitted, but had ſuffered death, as the bloody Biſhops earneſtly deſired; then had not the kingdom bin ſo ſurely, nor yet ſo purely kept and preſerved for his Majeſty and his royall Iſſue, as now it is, the Lord be praiſed therefore.</p>
            <p>Further I beſeech his right excellent Majeſty and Parliament to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that perſecution was the occaſion that the apoſtolick Church was at firſt ſcattered and driven into the wilderneſſe, that is, deſert places of the world; whither ſhe fled to ſave her ſelf from the rage and tyranny of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Rev. 12.6.14 &amp; 13.17.</p>
                  <p>2 Cor. 11.1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </note> and his Apoſtles and Miniſters, the firſt authors of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution under the goſpel: Therefore his Majeſty and Parliament may pleaſe to conſider, that ſo long as perſecution continue, ſo long will the apoſtolick Church continue ſcattered and perſecuted into the ſecret pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this world: and no marvail, for her faith and diſcipline is as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, as odious, and as unwelcome unto Antichriſt and his Biſhops and Miniſters now, as it was then, as their burning, baniſhing, hanging, and impriſoning do witneſſe even unto this day. And it is to be noted, that as the Apoſtolick faith and diſcipline (in the Apoſtles days,<note place="margin">2 Theſſ, 2.6, 7.</note> when through them true ſignes and wonders were wrought by the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gift and power of the holy Ghoſt) did let and hinder the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of iniquity wrought by Antichriſt his Apoſtles and Miniſters by whom the lying ſignes and wonders were done, through the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113439:12"/>
ſpirit of Satan.<note place="margin">
                  <p>2 Theſſ. 2.9 1 Tim. 4.1, 2, 3. 2 Tim. 3.1, 4, 5. &amp; 2 Pet. 2.1, 3. 1 Joh. 4.41. 2 John 7. Jud. 4 11.16, 18.</p>
                  <p>Note well. 1 Joh. 4 3.</p>
               </note> So now the catholick or antichriſtian faith and diſcipline (having gotten the upperhand by her lying ſigns &amp; wonders, and by perſecution) do by the ſame, let and hinder the myſtery of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, wrought by Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Miniſters, by whom the true ſignes and wonders were done without perſecution.</p>
            <p>And it is well worthy to be obſerved, both of King, Prince, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that the Biſhops, Miniſters of Antichriſt cannot abide, nor endure the faith and diſcipline of the apoſtolick Church, becauſe it will be the overthrow of their blaſphemous and ſpirituall Lordſhips, and of their Antichriſtian and bloudy kingdom. And therefore are they ſo fiery hot and zealous for the Catholick, or antichriſtian faith and diſcipline; for by their faith they ſhew plainly, that they are ſucceeded and deſcended from antichriſt, <hi>Who confeſſed not that the Meſſiah came in fleſh</hi>: and by their diſcipline or government they plainly ſhew they are Antichriſts Biſhops and Miniſters who perſecute with fire and ſword all degrees, both King, Prince and people, that will not confeſſe their faith, &amp; obey their diſcipline. And it is very plain and eaſie both for King, Prince, and people (if they will not take up Religion on credit, and content them with the religion they were born and brought up in (as do the Papiſts) to diſcern who they be that teach the apoſtolick faith and diſcipline, &amp; who they be that teach the Antichriſts faith and diſcipline, for the holy Apoſtle ſheweth it to all men that will give heed thereto; for he ſaith, <hi>Dearly beloved, beleeve not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits, whether they are of God, for many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world, which confeſſe not that Jeſus Meſſiah came in fleſh. Hereby ſhall you know the ſpirit of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Syriack <hi>ſaith,</hi> Came in fleſh.</note> 
               <hi>every ſpirit that confeſſeth that Ieſus Meſſiah came in fleſh is of God; and every ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus Meſſiah came in fleſh, is not of God: but this is the ſpirit of Antichriſt, whom ye have heard how that he ſhould come, and now already is he in the world. The ſame is the Antichrist that denyeth the Father and the Son; whoſoever denyeth the Son, the ſame hath not the Father</hi>:<note place="margin">
                  <p>1 Ioh. 2.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, 2<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Iohn 17.3.5.8.</p>
                  <p>1 Cor. 15.47 Iohn 6.38.4<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 62 &amp; 7.26, 27. Iohn 16.2. 3.27, 21.</p>
               </note> the Apoſtle meaneth ſuch <hi>as deny Jeſus to be Meſſiah, the Lord that came down from heaven,</hi> as Chriſt and they have taught, ſuch have not the Father, but doe deny him alſo as they have taught him; and therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The times ſhall come, that whoſoever killeth you, will think that he doth God good ſervice, but theſe things they will do unto you, becauſe thay have not known the father nor me, the father loveth ſuch as beleeve that I came out from God,</hi> thus ſaith Chriſt; but Antichriſt and his Miniſters beleeve not this doctrine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they thus teach <hi>Chriſt Jeſus the Meſſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113439:13"/>And you may pleaſe to underſtand that of this Antichriſt (or rather as the <hi>Syriack</hi>) of this falſe Chriſt came the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>: whoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters teach not this doctrine, and as the mother, ſo the daughter alſo, teacheth not this doctrine: but will likewiſe perſecute both Prince and people, that ſhall <hi>confeſſe that Ieſus Meſſiah came in fleſh as John teacheth</hi>;<note place="margin">
                  <p>1 Ioh. 4 2. Iohn 6.62. and 3.13. Iohn 17 5. 1 Cor. 15.47, 49</p>
                  <p>1 Ioh. 4, 3. 2 Cor. 11 12, 15.</p>
                  <p>Rev. 12.6.14.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>or that the Son of man aſcended up, where he was before, or that he was glorified with his father before the world was,</hi> as himſelf ſaith. <hi>Or that he was the ſecond man the Lord from heaven</hi>; or that he had, and hath a heavenly body, as <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth: for theſe and ſuch like doctrines doe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and her daughters perſecute with fire and ſword, being indued with the ſpirit of Antichriſt: By which Antichriſt his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Miniſters, the Apoſtolick Church was ſcattered and driven into the wilderneſſe, that is, deſert and ſecret places of this world, even by their bloody perſecution, the which ſtill they continue and raiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the members and witneſſes thereof, who were, and are the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs which in all ages have and doe ſuffer death, impriſonment and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ſince the firſt perſecution; and we never, read, nor ever ſhall read that the Apoſtolick Church, or ſuch as have derived their faith, and diſcipline of her, did ever perſecute.</p>
            <p>Therefore I humbly deſire his Majeſty and Parliament, with all godly carefulneſſe to conſider that it is not poſſible that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (called Catholick) or thoſe that are deſcended of her, and have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their Miniſtry and Ordination from her, ever was, or could be the apoſtolick Church (called primitive Church) or ſhe that is deſcended from her: ſeeing the Scripture ſaith the Apoſtolick Church (called in Scripture the woman) hath a place prepared of God in the wilderneſſe a thouſand two hundred and ſixty days <hi>from the preſence of ſuch as did perſecute her.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12 6.13.14.</note> How then, I beſeech you conſider, may it be poſſible that the church of Rome (called in Scripture a <hi>myſtery, great Babylon, the mother of whoredoms and abominations of the earth, the woman that ſitteth upon a ſcarlet coloured beaſt, ful of names of blaſphemy, the woman arrayed in purple &amp; ſcarlet, and guilded with gold and precious ſtones and pearls, having a cup of gold in her hand; full of abominations and ſilibineſſe of her fornication, the woman that is drunken with the blood of ſaints, &amp; with the blood of the martyrs or witneſſes of Ieſus</hi> by her beaſtly perſecution) was, or could be ever the Apoſtolique Church, or are thoſe that are deſcended from her ſeeing the Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">Rev. 12 6.13.14</note> 
               <hi>ſhe hath a place in the wilderneſſe prepared of God, where ſhe ſhould be ſed a thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes, from the preſence of her perſecutors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſo be, you will have the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe that are deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113439:13"/>
from her, to be the true Apoſtolick church:<note place="margin">Note.</note> then it wil follow that the church (called the woman, and did fly into the wilderneſs from her perſecutors) was, and is the falſe Antichriſtian Church; and alſo it will follow that thoſe (which we account to be the martyrs and witneſſes of Jeſus) were not of the true Apoſtolick Church,<note place="margin">
                  <p>2 Theſ. 2.3 6.8.</p>
                  <p>1 Tim. 4.1.2. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rev. 12.6. 11, 14. and 17.2, 6, 17. 2 Tim. 3.1.9. &amp; 4.3, 4. 2 Pet. 2.1.3 1 Ioh. 2.18, 19 and 4.1. 2 Iohn 7. Iude 4 11, 16.</p>
                  <p>Like mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like Daughter. 1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Rev. 2.24.</p>
               </note> but were obſtinate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and heretiques, even as their adverſaries (in <hi>Rome, Spain, England,</hi> and elſwhere) did perſecute, adjudge, and execute them for.</p>
            <p>But if you will have the prophecy of the Apoſtles to be true, and will beleeve their holy writings, and alſo will have the martyrs (that have been burned, baniſhed, hanged, impriſoned) to be of the true Apoſtolick Church, then it wil follow and that juſtly, according &amp; agreeable to the Scriptures, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe that did and doe perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, are deſcended from the falſe antichriſtian Church, called <hi>a myſtery, great Babylon, the mother of whordoms and abominations of the earth, &amp;c.</hi> which was and is drunken with <hi>the blood of ſaints and martyrs of Ieſus</hi>: ſeeing they have her antichriſtian faith and lordly diſcipline, and for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and maintenance thereof, will alſo burn, baniſh, hang and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; ſo hot and fiery zealous that thereby they ſhew plainly, that they walk ſo juſt and even in the ſteps and paths of the <hi>myſticall woman great Babylon, their bloody parent and mother</hi>: ſo even I ſay, as if they ſtudyed her <hi>lying and hypocriticall doctrine, her deep and deviliſh divinity, her blaſphemous princely and dangerous dignity; and her beaſtly, bloudy and deadly diſcipline.</hi> Through the continuance whereof, not only the Apoſtolick church is continued ſtill in the wildernes and deſert of this world, but alſo the Iews and others, both in great Britain and all over the world, are kept backe from the knowledge of Gods holy Word, the onely order and ordinance Chriſt hath appointed for the gathering of his Church together out of all places of the world.<note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1.</note> And ſo long as perſecution con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, you cannot try the ſpirits <hi>of the many falſe Prophets that are gone out into the world,</hi> as the holy Apoſtle doth lovingly adviſe and admoniſh you. But like the Papiſts,<note place="margin">Fire and ſword no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to the ſpirit and Word.</note> muſt be eyed onely to the ſpirits of your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Biſhops and their Miniſters, who will have all, both King, Prince, &amp; people to receive their ſpirits, and therefore will not have any others to preach and print within the land, leſt their lying doctrine and lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcipline be diſcovered and diſclaimed. And in ſtead of diſputing and writing by the word and ſpirit of Chriſt (againſt their adverſaries) they wil cruelly perſecute and fight againſt them by fire and ſword, and ſpirit of Antichriſt, from whom they are deſcended and ſucceeded, both lineally, and of great antiquity.<note place="margin">Myſtically.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113439:14"/>Wherefore I humbly beſeech the King and Parliament, that you will betimes liſten unto the holy ſpirit in the mouth of the prophet, which ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.10.</note> Be wiſe now therefore <hi>ye Kings, be learned (or inſtructed) ye Judges of the earth, ſerve the Lord in feare, and rejoice in trembling, kiſſe the Son of God leſt hee be angry, and ye periſh in the way of perſecution, when his wrath ſhall ſuddenly burn</hi>; Let not therefore <hi>the Kings of the earth band themſelves with the Biſhops and Miniſters of Antichriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3. 1 Ioh. 2.20. Rev. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>nor Princes aſſemble themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the Lord, and againſt his amointed,</hi> that is, againſt Chriſt and his Church; ſeeing both he and ſhe <hi>break your bands, and eaſt your cords from them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12.11.</note> Yea, her ſeed <hi>overcommeth you, by the bloud of the lamb, and by the word of their teſtimony, for they love not their lives unto death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beware then in time leſt you offend any more of theſe little <hi>ones that beleeve in Chriſt</hi>; ſeeing Chriſt ſaith, <hi>it were better to have a milſtone hanged about the neck,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 18.6.10.</note> 
               <hi>and drowned in the depth of the Sea, then ſo to do.</hi> He meaneth that it were better for you to loſe your lives, then any way to conſent to the offence of ſuch little ones that beleeve in Chriſt. See then I pray that they be not deſpiſed, burned, baniſhed, hanged and impriſoned. For their <hi>Angels alwaies behold the face of Chriſts Father in heaven</hi>; and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Matth. 10.38, 39.</p>
                  <p>Matth. 11.35.36</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>the tree is known by his fruit</hi>; but perſecuting of Chriſtians, is an evill fruit. <hi>And that a good man out of the good treaſure of his heart, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth good things: but perſecuting of chriſtians is no good thing: and that for every idle word men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall give accounts at the laſt day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> How much more for every wicked and cruel deed of perſecution, as burning, baniſhing, hanging and impriſoning of thoſe that confeſſe <hi>with the mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>and beleeve with the heart the Lord Ieſus, and that God raiſed him from the dead</hi>; whoſe laws and ordinances they are carefull to keepe and obey? Chriſt ſaith <hi>that ſuch ſhall be ſaved</hi>; and yet you feare not to burn, baniſh, hang, and impriſon ſuch. But if you beleeve that <hi>God will avenge his elect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 18.9.</note> beware of perſecuting his ſervants that cal on his name, ſpecially ſuch as witneſſe his truth againſt the <hi>abominations of Antichriſt.</hi> Suffer not your Biſhops to deſtroy thoſe men and women that ſtrive to ſerve God according to his will in his word. Be not your Biſhops exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners in burning, baniſhing, hanging, and impriſoning of harmleſſe and peaceable Chriſtians, but let them enjoy freedom of the goſpel, and liberty of conſcience; that ſo the apoſtolick Church (<hi>which is ſcattered and driven into the wilderneſſe</hi> and deſart of this world) may be againe gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, both of Jews and Gentiles, <hi>into viſible and stabliſhed congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.</note> And that <hi>the Catholick and univerſall Church of Antichriſt may bee conſumed and aboliſhed by his word and ſpirit, as the holy Apoſtle hath foretold,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113439:14"/>
even the uttermoſt of his arrivall, which is the Emperiall and triple Crowne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I pray the Lord to give ſuch grace, the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> may ebbe apate.</note> 
               <hi>through the triple ſea of</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>And again I humbly intreat the King and Parliament to vouchſafe to heare me with patience yet a little further: If freedom of the Goſpel, and permiſſion of conſcience might be granted, then would not Papiſts nor any others diſſemble their religion, to the diſhonor of God, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their ſouls, and to the great danger both of King and State, ſeeing they are forced to Church againſt their conſciences: &amp; may not Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuites (unawares to the Biſhops) become the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Miniſters, ſeeing the change of their Religion, and religious habit differ ſo little; and ſo by degrees infect the people with more Popiſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as occaſion ſhall be?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nota.</hi> From Popes ſubmiſſion there is great ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> And ſuch men will readily embrace the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Orders, and ſo they ſhall readily have the Biſhops favours: by which means they may more eaſily and ſpeedily have acceſſe unto the Court, and preſence of the King and Prince, which indeed is very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, howſoever not regarded. Therefore I doe (according to my duty) humbly adviſe his Majeſty not to beutifie his Court and preſence with any popiſh ſtones, not with one, though it be of Alablaſter.</p>
            <p>But permiſſion of conſcience and freedom, and liberty of the Goſpel, will no way be dangerous to the King or State, if ſuch like rules as theſe be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That no people tainted with treaſon doe beare any office.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all ſorts of people tainted with treaſon, do (at all times from home) weare a black hat with two white ſigns, the one before,<note place="margin">
                  <p>1 Kin. 2.36 41, 42.</p>
                  <p>Rom. 13 1. to 5.</p>
               </note> the other behind in open ſight.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That no people tainted with treaſon, approach within ten miles of the Court without licence.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no people tainted with treaſon, do inhabit the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> nor yet within ten miles thereof.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That none tainted with treaſon, do make any aſſembly or congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That no perſon or perſons (in whatſoever difference, by reaſoning or diſputing) do draw any weapon, nor give any blow, ſtroke, or puſh, in paine and penalty, as his Majeſty and Parliament thinke meet.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That (for the more peace and quietnes, and for the ſatisfying of the weak and ſimple, among ſo many perſons differing in Religion, it bee lawfull for every perſon or perſons, yea Jewes and Papiſts, to write,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113439:15"/>
diſpute, confer and reaſon, print and publiſh any matter touching. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, either for or againſt whomſoever, always provided they alledge no Fathers for proof of any point of religion,<note place="margin">
                  <p>2 Tim. 2.24, 25</p>
                  <p>Iames 3.17</p>
               </note> but only the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, neither yet to reproach or ſlander one another, nor any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, but with all love, gentleneſs, and peaceableneſs, informe one another to the glory of God honor of the King and State, and to their own good and credit;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> A true ſigne of falſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters</note> by which means, both few errors, and few books wil be written and printed, ſeeing all falſe Miniſters, and moſt people, have little or nothing elſe (beſides the Fathers) to build their religion and doctrine upon: or if it be once ſtabliſhed by law, that none ſhall confirm their religion and doctrine by the Fathers, and by priſons burning and baniſhing, &amp;c. but by the holy Scriptures, then error will not be written nor diſputed, except by obſtinate perſons, &amp; feared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, ſeeing the word of God will be no ſhelter for any error. Yea, I know by experience among the people called <hi>Browniſts,</hi> that a Man ſhal not draw them to write, though they be deſired; for one of their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers called <hi>Maſt. Rob.</hi> hath had a writing of mine in his hands, above ſix moneths,<note place="margin">Now above 12 months.</note> and as yet I can get no anſwer, it ſeemes hee knoweth not how better to hide his errors, then by ſilence, and this will bee the caſe of all falſe Biſhops and Miniſters,<note place="margin">Iohn 3.20. Iohn 3.10.</note> who had rather be mute and dumb, then to be drawn into the light with their errors.</p>
            <p>Therefore permiſſion of conſcience, and liberty of the goſpel in our land of great <hi>Britain,</hi> wil mightily further the advancement of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick faith: and chiefly their bookes, whereout ſufficient matter will be drawn for the convincing of every particular Religion which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Religion ſtabliſhed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who by all meanes lawfull, ſought the converſion and ſalvation both of Jewes and Gentiles.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.20.22. Act. 16.3.</note> And they are unconſtant and faith leſſe men, or at leaſt very ignorant, that think error will overcome and prevaile againſt the truth.</p>
            <p>For the aboliſhing of ſuch thoughts, I deſire ſuch men to conſider the mighty victory and prevailing of the truth, in the time of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, which (notwithſtanding reſiſted and diſputed againſt: by the moſt part of the Prieſts and learned men, both of Jewes and Gentiles) yet overcame and prevailed againſt all the errors of the high Prieſts, and great learnedmen, both of the Jews and Gentiles, and the Apoſtle faith, <hi>we cannot do any thing againſt the truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.8</note> 
               <hi>but for the truth</hi>: and ſeeing it is the ſame truth w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> all good men would embrace, why ſhould wee not hope the ſame victory by it? Did not King <hi>Darius</hi> &amp; all the people both Iew
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113439:15"/>
and gentils cry out and ſay, <hi>that truth is great and ſtrongeſt</hi>?<note place="margin">1 Eſd. 4.38.41.</note> Why then ſhould thoſe that have the truth, and thoſe that would have the truth, be afraid of error? ſeeing truth diſcovereth dark and dangerous wayes of error, though abroad in open books, even as light diſcovereth dark and dangerous places, though abroad in open high wayes: And as the more darke and dangerous the wayes be, the more neceſſary &amp; need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full will light be found of all that travel: So the more darke and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous the errors be, the more needfull and profitable wil truth be found, of al that would travel to heaven. But ſome may object and ſay, <hi>let all this be granted, yet it is no wiſedom we think, to bring dangerous errors into the light, that ſo many men may ſtumble at them. Which being not brought to light, would not be ſo much as known to ſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, no more, then a Rock that lyeth hid under water,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> which (for want of bringing into the light) many men may make Shipwrack there on, and ſo ſtumble or fall nevertheleſſe, though it be not ſo much as known to them before. Therefore as a Rock in the Seas (though not ſo much as known to ſome) yet (for want of being made known) many men ſtumble and fal thereon, and ſo periſh both men and goods: So an error (though not ſo much as known to ſome) yet for want of being made known, many men may ſtumble and fall thereon, and ſo periſh both bodies and ſoules, the which is more lamentable. And as Rocks in the Seas, the more they manifeſt themſelves; So errors in the world the more they manifeſt themſelves, the more furtherance in the way to heaven. And you ſhall underſtand that errors being brought to the light of the word of God, will vaniſh as darknes before the light of a torch: even as the chaffe before the winde cannot ſtand, ſo error before truth cannot abide: therefore it is no hinderance, but a great furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to have all erroneous Rocks in the haven to heaven, made knowen and publiſhed.</p>
            <p>And a great and ſure argument it is,<note place="margin">Another true ſigne of falſe miniſters.</note> that thoſe Biſhops and Miniſters have not the truth, that publikely dare not diſpute or write againſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, as may be ſeene in the Biſhops &amp; miniſters in Queen Maries dayes, which could not abide to have books written &amp; Printed, of that which they called error and hereſie, but cauſed, that if any ſuch were written, both them and the Authors to be burned, if they could come by them. Therefore if permiſſion of conſcience and libertie of the Goſpel be not granted, and burning lawes repealed, then the Biſhops &amp; miniſters now may perſwade and cauſe to be burned, both the Books the &amp; Authors, that have the truth inſtead of hereſy and hereticks, even as their prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113439:16"/>
have done already,<note place="margin">The Word of God the onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the faith of Chriſt.</note> and ſo ſhed more innocent bloud, and alſo provoke the Lord to further wrath againſt the King and State. It is not the gallowes, nor the priſons, nor burning, nor baniſhing, that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Apoſtolick faith: indeed the King and State may defend Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions peace by their ſword &amp; civil power, but not the faith, otherwiſe, then by the word and ſpirit of God. The dutch Princes and Peeres ſay, <hi>that force ſword, &amp; gallows, in matter of religion, is a good meanes to ſpil bloud, and make an uprore in the land, but not to bring any man from one faith to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The Pagans will not perſecute one another for religion, though (as I read) there be above three thouſand ſorts among them. And you know both King Henry &amp; Queen Mary, thought themſelves defenders of the faith, and though they burned hereticks and hereſy, when they burned Men and their books,<note place="margin">Idol Biſhops and falſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of perſecution Rev. 16.14.</note> but now you ſee and muſt acknowledge, that they were peeſecutors of the faith, inſtead of defenders therof, and alſo that they (through the inſtigation of their bloudy Biſhops) burned the word of God, and thoſe that profeſſed and wrought it, inſtead of hereſy and hereticks. And thus it will be now if the Biſhops and their Miniſters may have their wils: and therein they (as their predeceſſors) fulfill the word of God, <hi>in gathering Kings of the earth to the battell of the great day of God Almighty.</hi> For they perſwade Kings to force their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.17.</note> to receive the faith, and to be of the Church, whereas the word of God teacheth otherwiſe, ſaying, <hi>Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God,</hi> and not by the Kings ſword. And Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Teach of nations, and not force all nations</hi>: and this teaching is to be underſtood by the word and writing of the Prophets and Apoſtles of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt, which is the Word of God For they that wil be of the true Faith and Church, muſt be called thereunto, out of the World by the Word of God, in every nation, and not forced and conſtrained in every nation, as the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all other falſe Biſhops and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters have and doe perſwade Kings, Emperors and Magiſtates.</p>
            <p>And his Majeſty and Parliament may pleaſe to underſtand, that ſo to do,<note place="margin">Mat. 16. 16. 1 Theſ. 5.19.</note> is to quench the <hi>Spirit of God, in Chriſts Biſhops and Miniſters,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to fruſtrate the precept of Chriſt which ſaith: <hi>Preach the Goſpel to every creature.</hi> Beſides it maketh their one office &amp; function void, they ought <hi>to preach and inſtruct with al meeknes them that are contrary minded, proving if God at any time wil give them repentance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>that they may know the truth: for the miniſters of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be apt to teach, gentle towards all men, ſuffering evil men patiently,</hi> telling Kings and Princes, that the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of <hi>Chriſt Biſhops and Miniſters are not carnal</hi> (as the weapons of all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113439:16"/>
falſe &amp; Antichriſtian Biſhops and Miniſters are) but <hi>Spiritual, and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through God, to caſt downe holds, caſting downe every high thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.3.5.</note> 
               <hi>that is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought, to the obedience of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, if al within the land be forced to be of the church as the Biſhops and their miniſters would ſtil have it, then there would be no world in the land, but al the land would be the Church, which is abſurd &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſcriptures, and great ignorance do the Biſhops,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Rev. 11.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Act. 2.41 47.</p>
                  <p>Note. Act. 2.47.</p>
               </note> &amp; their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhew, when they think the whole nation of people is the church of Chriſt, for then it cannot be ſaid, <hi>out of great Britaine, the Lord added to the Church from day to day, ſuch as ſhould be ſaved:</hi> ſeeing within the land there would be none without to be added: Alſo within that land,<note place="margin">
                  <p>A true Church wil not perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute. Mat. 12.25. Rev. 18.2.8. 1 Cor. 8.11.12.</p>
                  <p>Luc. 10.3. Gen. 32.28. Rom. 13.4.</p>
               </note> there would be no perſecution, ſeeing the church of Chriſt doth not perſecute at al, much leſſe it ſelf, but the Miniſters and members of that Church do perſecute one another; and therefore it cannot be the ſpiritual King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; Church of Chriſt, but of Antichriſt, ſeeing it is divided againſt it ſelf, and perſecuteth one another and wil with her mother, <hi>great Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon be conſumed and condemned,</hi> ſeeing (as ſhe) they burne, baniſh, hang, and impriſon one another, which is no Chriſtian, but Antichriſtian, monſtrous, cruel, woolviſh &amp; tyranous part and practiſe, for <hi>Chriſt ſent his Miniſters as lambs among wolves and not as wolves among Lambs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, I humbly and with al reverence do beſeech his right excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty, to give me leave, to put him in minde, of thoſe things that do concern the glory of God, the aſſurance of his owne ſalvation, the ſtabliſhment of his throne, &amp; the benefit both of the Church of Chriſt, and the common wealth of al his Dominions. And though as <hi>Joſias,</hi> he finde (by reading in the booke of the New Teſtament) a great alteration of the Apoſtolick faith, <hi>&amp; change of the lawes &amp; ordinances of Chriſt, within his Dominions</hi>; Yet not to be diſmayed, as <hi>Henry Legrand,</hi> but be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as <hi>Joſiah</hi> to labour &amp; endeavour the redreſſe thereof, according to the minde of Chriſt, in his New Teſtament. And I doubt not, but as <hi>Iacob the Patriarch prevailed with God &amp; men: ſo ſhal Iacob the King prevails both with God &amp; men, eſpecially being his chief ſteward</hi> by his new teſtament.</p>
            <p>Through the zealous reading whereof will be found, that Antichriſt the King of the Catholick faith &amp; diſcipline (called the myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.) <hi>doth ſit in the Temple of God,</hi> even as the Scripture hath foretold.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 1 Tim 4. Rev. 7 15. 2 The. 2.8. Rev. 17.16.17.</note> But it is to be noted that the Scripture hath alſo foretold, of the <hi>conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation &amp; abolition, of this antichriſt the man of ſin, and his miſtery of iniquity, with the utmoſt of his arrival, or higheſt top of dignity, he is come unto</hi>: and this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113439:17"/>
ſhall be done by the <hi>ſpirit of the Lord in the much of his ſervants. For when the words of God be fulfilled,</hi> then ſhal the ſervants of the Lord prevaile (by his word &amp; ſpirit) <hi>with ten Kings that ſhal hate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>C<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aled the Temple of God.</p>
                  <p>2 Theſ. Rev. 17.1.1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.18. Ioh. 16.2</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>and make the whore deſolate, which ſitteth in the hearts and conſciences of peoples, multitudes &amp; nations, and this whore is the woman called the great City which reigneth over the Kings of the earth,</hi> meaning the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by her falſe faith and diſcipline, which is ſo fa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſetled in the hearts &amp; conſciences of <hi>the Kings of the earth, that they think they do God good ſervice, in killing &amp; burning his ſervants that do ſpeak againſt her faith and di<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cipline, and that wil not buy any of her war<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.13 14.</note> her Antichriſtian doctrines and ordinances. But as ſhe hath had <hi>her exa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tation and arrival to the height and dignity of the ſea Empire of Rome,</hi> by the love of kings, <hi>who have given their power and authority unto her,</hi> and who have fought for <hi>her against the Saints &amp; ſervants of Ieſus</hi>: So ſhe ſhal have her conſummation &amp; abolition (<hi>from that height and dignity</hi>) by the hatred of Kings, who againe ſhall take their power and authority from her, and therewith defend the <hi>peace and perſons of the Saints and ſervants of Ieſus: and not for religions peace,</hi> will uſe their power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt the bloudy perſecution of Antichriſt and al his bloudy Biſhops and Miniſters, and ſo become nurſing fathers unto the Church of Chriſt. And as it hath pleaſed God, to give his Majeſty peace round about, as he did unto King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in whoſe dayes the <hi>material Temple be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be repaired</hi> (which was a figure of the ſpiritual temple:) So I pray it may pleaſe him alſo (in the peaceable dayes of King <hi>James) to begin to repaire the ſpiritual Temple</hi>) the Apoſtolick church ſcattered and driven abroad into the wildernes of this world,<note place="margin">Eſa. 2.4. Ezra 4.7. Ha. 24.10</note> whoſe calling and gathering together, muſt be by the preaching of the word of God, both to Jewes and Gentils, and not by the ſword <hi>of the Kings of the earth, as Antichriſt's and his Ministers</hi> have now along time perſwaded &amp; prevailed, whereby not onely the Jewes and infidels, but alſo papiſts and other falſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, are hindred and deprived from the knowledge of the Apoſtolick faith. And it is to be noted that <hi>David</hi> might not build Gods Temple, becauſe he had ſpilt much blood, which ſheweth, <hi>no blood ought to be ſpilt for the building of the ſpirituall temple.</hi> 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.3. <hi>Ergo</hi> peace in religion is a good meanes to make a unity of religion among ſo many Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſects.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 25.2. and 35.5. Act 2.40.41. Mat. 28</note>And it is wel worthy conſideration, that as in the time of the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, the lord would not have his offerings by conſtraint, <hi>but of every man whoſe heart gave it freely</hi>: ſo now in time of the goſpel he will not have the people conſtrain'd, <hi>but as many as receive the word gladly, they are to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113439:17"/>
be added to the church by baptiſm</hi>:<note place="margin">Mat. 16.16. Mat. 10.11 14.</note> 
               <hi>and therefore Chriſt commanded his diſciples to teach all nations, and baptize them, that is, to preach the word of ſalvation to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very creature of all ſorts of nations, that are worthy and willing to receive it</hi>: and ſuch as ſhal willing &amp; gladly receive it, he hath commanded to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in the water, that is, dipped for dead in the water; and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Elſe what ſhall they do, who are baptized for dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19 Rom. 6.4. Col. 2.12. Luke 8.37.</note> 
               <hi>if the dead be not raiſed, why are they baptized for dead</hi>? And therefore he ſaith, <hi>we are buried then with him by baptiſm, &amp;c.</hi> and it is to be wel obſerved, that when Chriſt would have preached the word of ſalvation to the <hi>Gada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> he did not compell them when they refuſed, but finding them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to receive him and his word,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.54.55.</note> he turned from them without hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them: alſo when <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaw <hi>that ſome of the Samaritans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Chriſt, they would have commanded fire from heaven to conſume them, as</hi> Elias <hi>did, but Chriſt rebuked them and ſaid, Ye Know no of what ſpirit are, for the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> By all which it may pleaſe his Majeſty and Parliament, to take knowledg that <hi>Christ will have none conſumed with fire and ſword, for not hearing and not receiving his Word.</hi> And that (howſoever it hath been the mind of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt to deſtroy mens lives for Religion, and therein have not ſpared neither Prince no people) yet it is not the mind of Chriſt that Princes ſhould deſtroy their ſubjects, nor yet that Subjects ſhould deſtroy their Princes for difference in Religion.</p>
            <p>And therefore why ſhould Biſhops perſwade Princes and people, and why ſhould King, Prince and people be perſwaded by their Biſhops and Miniſters to be contrary minded to Chriſt? verily it is a notorious and plaine token of a falſe faith and diſcipline, that is defended by fire and ſword, the power and authority of Princes: And they cannot be <hi>Chriſts</hi> Biſhops and preachers,<note place="margin">Chriſts Bps. will not bee Lords ever the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</note> that perſwade Princes and peoples to ſuch anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian tyranny and cruelty. And it is very evident that thoſe Biſhops and Miniſters which give over men and women to the Magiſtrate to be perſwaded by perſecution, doe ſhew clearly that their doctrine is not good, and that they want the word and ſpirit of God, and therefore flee to the Magiſtrates ſword for the forcing of them to their faith and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline: and as the wine is not good which we are forced to drink; ſo thoſe doctrines are not good which we are forced to beleeve. But it may be by this time all thoſe Biſhops (who unfainedly fear God, and truly love the King) wil haſte and make ſpeed to come unto his Majeſty for pardon, acknowledging the truth of this book, confeſſing their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and arrogance, in the knowledge of Gods word, and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113439:18"/>
the people to heare the word preached; and for impriſoning, burning, baniſhing and hanging for Religion, contrary to the mind of Chriſt, and alſo for ſtopping the mouths of men, and burning their books, that preach and write contrary to their minds and wils; yea, it may be they will alſo confeſſe and ſay, <hi>Oh moſt gracious King, we beſeech your Majeſty to ſhew us mercy, and to forgive us our ſpirituall pride and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that we have thus long uſurped the blaſphemous titles of ſpirituall Lords and Lords graces, the which titles, we now to the glory of God, and honor of the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>oe know in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences that this is true.</p>
                  <p>Iob. 32.22. Phil 2.9.11</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>do with unfained hearts confeſſe to be due, and belong onely to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: and that the name and title of ſpirituall Lord cannot belong to any earthly creature, no not to the King or Emperor, becauſe it is an heavenly name and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, how much leſſe can it belong, or be due unto us, your Majeſties unworthy ſubjects and ſcholars? And for ſo much as we now underſtand (the Lord be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therefore) that the holy and heavenly name and divine title of ſpirituall Lord is as much, yea as high and great as the name and title of a ſpirituall God &amp; alſo that it is a name above every name, which God the Father hath given unto Chriſt onely to the end, that every knee ſhould how unto that onely and heavenly name, and that every tongue ſhould confeſſe that Ieſus is the Meſſiah, the Lord, unto the glory of God the Father, that in all things Chriſt might have the preheminence; for be alone is the head of the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>which is his body: the which cannot bee, ſo long as we, or any other Biſhops do hold and retain that divine, high, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellent name and title of ſpirituall Lord; becauſe then it cannot be ſaid that God hath ſo highly exalted him, as to give him a name above every name, ſeeing our names and titles are alſo ſpirituall, and are called ſpirituall Lords ſo well as the ſon of God, Ieſus the meſſiah: the remembrance hereof, moſt gracious ſoveraign, do make us to tremble before God and the King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Bps. in titles equall to the ſonne of God.</note> 
               <hi>And therefore we muſt earneſtly deſire your ſacred Majeſty and the whole Parliament to diſcharge and releaſe us of theſe fearfull names and titles that do onely belong to the ſon of God, Ieſus, the onely ſpirituall Lord that God hath given unto his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les theſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, who are exalted above all earthly Gods.</note>
               <hi>Moreover, we do (according to the truth) acknowledge, that if we ſhould any longer retaine theſe divine and high names of ſpiritual Lords and Lords graces, we ſhould therein be intituled, not only with a name equall to our Lord Ieſus, the onely begotten ſon of God, but alſo we ſhould be intituled with a name and title above your right excellent Majesty, yea above all Emperors, Kings, and Princes of the earth, the which alone we doe acknowledge to bee a ſufficient cauſe to put us down, and to deprive us of theſe uſurped names and blaſphemous titles. Alſo we do confeſſe that our pomp and ſtate wherein we now live, is more like the Biſhops of the Catholick church of Antichriſt, then any way like the Biſhops of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Church of Chriſt, unto whom we acknowledge we ought to be made like,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113439:18"/>
and alſo to be qualified with the like gifts and graces of the Spirit, or elſe in no caſe we can be meet Biſhops for the Church of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle plainely tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth both to</hi> Timothy <hi>and</hi> Titus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. Tith. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>And we muſt further acknowledge and confeſſe, that our houſes, houſholds, and revenues, are more fit and meet for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Dukes, and Earls, then for the Biſhops of Chriſt. Wherfore (being moved and ſtirred up hereto by the feare of God) we earneſtly beſeech your Majeſty and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament alſo to disburden us of this great pomp and ſtate, and of our great and princelike houſes, houſholds and revenues, that ſo we may be made equall and conformable to the miniſters of Chriſt, and then we ſhal have both hope and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the world to come, although but little in this, except your Majeſty and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament do grant free liberty of conſcience, the which wee now doe alſo with the poor diſtreſſed chriſtians moſt humbly intreat and deſire; and that for theſe foure reaſons: Firſt, becauſe thereby the goſpel of Chriſt will be ſet free and at liberty, whereby all people both Iews and Gentiles wil be gathered to the apoſtolick faith, church and diſcipline. Secondly, becauſe many of your Majeſties ſubjects, both men and women (who now are forced to diſſemble their Religion, for fear of our perſecution) will be releaſed and ſet free from their ſpirituall bondage and ſlavery, wherein we now doe hold them againſt their conſciences, and ſo they will become more faitfull Chriſtians to God, and more loyall ſubjects to your Majeſty then ever they were before, to the ſalvation of their ſoules, and the ſafety of the Crown and State. Thirdly, becauſe the poore diſtreſſed Chriſtians (how bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and diſperſed out of their Fatherland, over the face of the earth) will bee redeemed from great miſery and bondage, wherein now (no doubt) they live and abide, becauſe they will not bee in bondage to any other ſpirituall Lord or bead, then the Lord Ieſus Meſſiah alone; whoſe faith and diſcipline they deſire onely to learne and obey. Fourthly, becauſe thereby great benefit and commodity will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound both to your Majeſty and to all your ſubjects within your Highneſs do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions by the great commerce, in trade and trafick both of Iewes and all people, which now for want of liberty of conſcience, are forced and driven elſwhere: and alſo from the revenues and livings which we and our Clergy doe poſſeſſe, and from the Courts and offices we hold and keep greats profit and commodity will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound, both to your Highneſſe, and to all your kingdoms; we ſay, more profit and commodity then we or any man is able to expreſſe. And therefore we alſo deſire all his Majeſties ſubjects hath great and ſmall in all love and feare of God, not to be offended, or any way moved or grieved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Too great is the ods to uſe the ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Word.</note> 
               <hi>when they ſhall ſee ſuch a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d formati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of us, as that famous King</hi> Henry <hi>the eight did make of our lordly brethren the Abbots and their Clergy. For indeed ſuch a reformation ought to come among us and our Clergy, ſeeing we are no way agreeable to the new Testament, of the onely ſpirituall Lord Ieſus Meſſiah, but are limbs and fellow members of that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113439:19"/>
Antichriſtian and Romiſh church, which in the ſcriptures is Prophecyed to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed and deſtroyed Now therefore we pray you all let not King</hi> David <hi>ſay, the ſons of</hi> Zerviah <hi>are too ſtrong for him, for that will be unprofitable for you all.</hi> And for concluſion, we entreat his Majeſty and Parliament to enact, that as our adverſaries come againſt us onely with the word of God, ſo we go againſt them onely with the word of God, and nor as we have done by civill authority, for ſo our ſelves may be forced to diſſemble: Thus it may be the Lord will perſwade and work in the hearts of ſome of the Biſhops who will willingly reſign their Antichriſtian titles and Popiſh pomp and ſtate, with their princelike houſes and livings into the hands of the King, without any <hi>compulſion or conſtraint.</hi> But if they do not, yet if it pleaſe God to open the Kings heart to ſee their <hi>Antichriſtian and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol estate,</hi> &amp; the danger and damage they cauſe both to the King, Prince, &amp; people, they will be compelled thereto even as their lordly brethren the Abbots in King <hi>Henry</hi>'s days were.<note place="margin">The Bps. greater I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols then the Abbots, images, or golden calf.</note> And howſoever it be not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or perhaps not diſcerned, yet in the ſight of God and his people they are greater Idols then their lordly brethren the Abbots: yea, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Idols then the images of wood and ſtone (which that famous and godly King <hi>Edward</hi> did pul down and deſtroy) for they did not impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor burn, nor hang, nor yet cauſe to bee baniſhed any of the Kings ſubjects, thus would not worſhip them as theſe Idol-biſhops do: and out of doubt, theſe Biſhops are greater Idols then the golden Calfe <hi>Airon</hi> made and offered unto, for the Calf did not perſecute nor vex ſuch as did not acknowledge it for their Lord, as the Biſhops doe: neither did the Calf reign and rule by force over the conſciences of the people, as theſe Idol-biſhops doe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Calf was ſet up in ſtead of <hi>Moſes, who brought the people out of Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex. 32.1, 7. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter idolatry then to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey other ſpirituall Lords then the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?</note> 
               <hi>and ſhewed them the will of God</hi>; but theſe Biſhops are ſet up in ſtead of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who have brought us out of the bondage of hel, and who ſheweth us his Fathers will in his new Teſtament, the which theſe Idol-biſhops will not ſuffer us to obey, but in ſtead thereof will force us to fal down, worſhip and obey their father Antichriſts wil and old teſtament, which ſtinks in the noſtrills of all reformed ſtrangers that hear there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as well as in ours that have taken our flight from it. Therefore theſe ſpirituall lords and Idol-biſhops, ought to be pulled down and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,<note place="margin">2 Kings 23 17.20</note> like the Abbots their lordly brethren, though not ſacrificed unto the Lord in <hi>Smithfield, as the godly King Joſias ſacrificed the Idol-prieſts of the high places on the Altars thereof.</hi> And I do verily beleeve, that if free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of conſcience be granted, that the ſpiritual kingdom of theſe Idol-biſhops,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113439:19"/>
will in time fall to the ground of it ſelf,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 5.3.</note> as the Idol Dagon fell before the Ark: for through the knowledge of Gods word will all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people withdraw themſelves in all peaceable and godly wife, from the ſpirituall obedience of theſe ſpirituall Lords and Idol-biſhops, and quietly betake themſelves unto the obedience of the only ſpiritual Lord <hi>Ieſus Meſſiah.</hi> But howſoever it be, I ſhall be contented therewith, and ſo I wiſh a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l others, for we all ought to be content if we obtain liberty of conſcience; and therefore to give God praiſe continually, that hath wrought ſo bleſſed a work in the hearts of the King and Parliament, for whom, as the Scripture teacheth, wee ought to <hi>make ſupplications,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tit. 2.1.2</note> 
               <hi>prayers, and interceſſions, that they may come to the knowledge of the truth, and that we may lead a peaceable and quiet life in all godlineſſe and honeſty.</hi> And unto whom we ought to give (by the law of God) all earthly honour,<note place="margin">Ro. 13.1.7.</note> fear and reverence, and willingly to pay tribute and cuſtome, tax and toll, ſo much, and ſo often as it ſhall pleaſe his Majeſty and Parliament to appoint and gather by any officer or officers whatſoever. For whom alſo, and for the whole common-wealth of all his kingdoms, we ought to be diligent and ready to hazard and lay down not only our goods, but alſo our lives at all times and occaſions. For Chriſt hath onely ſet us free from all eccleſiaſticall laws and ordinances, which himſelfe hath not commanded in his laſt will and teſtament: yea, from the eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call laws and commandments of the old Teſtament,<note place="margin">Col. 2.14. Heb. 8.23.</note> how much more hath he ſet us free from the eccleſiaſticall laws and ordinances of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? but he hath not ſet us free from the morall and judiciall law of God, for that the King is bound to execute, and we are bound to obey: and for want of the execution thereof,<note place="margin">Deut 17.18 20</note> there are in our land many whores and whorekeepers, and many children murdered, beſides the death and undoing of many perſons about whores. Wherefore I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire that the morall and judicial law of God may be practiſed and executed, of all degrees, both high and low, without reſpect of perſons, according to the mind of Chriſt: for the Lord will have that every man ſhall love him above all, and his neighbor as himſelf, and Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.31.</note> As ye would that men ſhould do to you, ſo do yet to them likewiſe.</p>
            <p>Therfore as the King would not have his ſubjects to take away his life becauſe he is contrary to them in religion: ſo let not the King take away his ſubjects lives, becauſe they are contrary to the king in religion: &amp; as you would not that men ſhould force you to a religion againſt your conſciences, ſo do not you force men to a religion againſt their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: and as it is the duty of ſubjects to ſeek the converſion of their king
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113439:20"/>
&amp; State by the word of God, and not his and their deſtruction by fire and ſword; So it is the duty of the King and State, to ſeek the converſion of their Subjects by the word of God, and not their deſtruction by fire and ſword as the Pope and his Prelates doe teach:<note place="margin">Note</note> whoſe vaſſals therein both Emperors and Kings (as well as people) have beene a long time: both to the deſtruction of themſelves &amp; their ſubjects. For who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that Prelates and prieſts have perſwaded Subjects, to deſtroy their Kings and Princes, as wel as Kings &amp; Princes to deſtroy their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.17 &amp; 6.19.20</note> but I pray them both to take notice that the Scripture ſaith <hi>he that destroyeth the Temple of God, him will God destroy.</hi> Let not therefore Kings, Princes, nor Subjects bee any longer perſwaded to deſtroy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the ſubtletie of Biſhops and their miniſters, who (moſt of them) onely ſeeke the ſecurity of their owne pompe and glory, and the ſtabliſhment of their ſpiritual thrones therein; for ſo long as they may confirm that, they paſſe not who periſh, whether King, Prince or people. Again therefore I humbly pray his Majeſty and Parliament, to repeale and make void all popiſh lawes and canons, and to ſee the <hi>moral &amp; Iudiciall law of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Frederick</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn Palſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graves,</hi> ſaid that under pretext of the holy-ghoſts office of correction little elſe was ſought then to reigne over the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Magiſtrates &amp; ſubjects like as in the accurſed popedom is come to paſſe &amp;c.</note> both firmly enacted, and carefully practiſed after the minde of Chriſt: and them ſhall <hi>Chriſts ſpirituall throne be ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the hearts and conſciences both of King, Prince, and People,</hi> ſo as the Church Chriſts ſpirituall Kingdom ſhall increaſe in the knowledge of faith, and obedience thereof, with all love, peace and charity, one towards another. And the common wealth of his Majeſties Kingdoms will flouriſh and proſper, and alſo his <hi>throne be conſtantly ſtabliſhed</hi> both to him and his Heires throughout all his Dominions, in a ſure land of peace and love, th'one with and towards another, to the glory of God and the comfort of his Majeſty and of all his Subjects, and alſo to a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and excellent glorious pattern of government, to all Kingdoms, Nations, and Countries round about, as in the daies of <hi>Salomon King of Iſrael.</hi> For if the holy lawes of Gods word be practiſed and executed after <hi>Chriſts</hi> will, then ſhall neither King, Prince nor people be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for difference in Religion, then <hi>Treaſon and Rebellion,</hi> as well as burning, baniſhing, hanging, or impriſoning, for difference in religion will ceaſe and be laid down, then ſhall not men, women, and youth be hanged for theft then ſhall not the poor ſame, ſick, and weak ones, be ſtocked and whipped, neither ſhall the poore, ſtranger, fatherleſſe, and windowes be driven to beg from place to place, neither ſhall the lame, ſick, and weake perſons ſuffer ſuch miſery &amp; be forſaken of their kindred, as now they be, then ſhall not murder, whoredome, and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113439:20"/>
be bought out for money: then ſhall not the great defraud and wrong the ſmall, neither the rich oppreſſe the poore by uſury and little wages: then ſhall not men bring up and inherit others children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of their owne, neither ſhall an honeſt man be forced to live with a whore inſtead of an honeſt wife, nor yet an honeſt woman be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to live with a whorekeeper in ſtead of an honeſt husband. Then ſhal not ſervants be forced from marriage by bonds, nor yet be bound to ſervitude, longer then ſix yeers, neither ſhal they be brought up contrary to covenant, nor poſted from one quarter or one yeare to another for their freedom and in the end be forced to buy it of their Maſters, or elſe to goe without it too. Then ſhall neither Prince nor people be diſinherited, for not being of the Church:<note place="margin">Note wel.</note> neither ſhall they be held lawleſſe perſons, though excommunicated: neither ſhal any man dare kil them as now they may, and be quit by law: neither ſhall any man feare to have his mouth ſtopt for preaching the truth: then ſhall no man need to flee out of his native Countrey and Fatherland, for perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake: then ſhall all men live in peace under his owne vine,<note place="margin">Act. 15.28.29. &amp; 21.25</note> laud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and praiſing God, honoring and obeying the King. Then alſo will no bloud be eaten among Chriſtians, whereby the Jewes ſhould have juſt cauſe to ſtumble or be offended, neither ſhould any reliques of the ceremoniall law, (as Tithes and offerings &amp;c.) be any longer in uſe, whereby the Jewes ſhould be hardned in their unbeliefe,<note place="margin">Jewes kept back from the faith by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and kept from the faith of the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> Then ſhall the Jewes inhabit &amp; dwel under his Majeſties Dominion, to the great profit of his Realmes, and to their furtherance in the faith: the which we are bound to ſeeke in all love and peace, ſo well as others, to our utmoſt endeavour, for Chriſt hath commanded to <hi>teach all nations &amp;c.</hi> and they are the firſt. Laſtly, then ſhall not ſo many Men and Women be deceived by falſe Miniſters, neither by their Sermons, nor yet by their bookes, which are full fraighted with falſe doctrines, and confirmed and countenanced, not onely by the Kings authority and power, but alſo by wreſting and falſe interpreting of the Scriptures, and by alledging of popiſh Fathers, which through the great ignorance of the people doe greatly prevaile: btt then ſhall be aboliſhed through the word and ſpirit of god (his two witneſſes) in the mouth of his ſervants,<note place="margin">Rev. 11.3. and 19.10.</note> who by word and writing ſhall breed ſuch knowledge, that none of wiſedomes children ſhall be deceived. Another reaſon, why ſo many good people are now deceived, is, becauſe we that have moſt truth are moſt perſecuted; and therefore moſt poore, whereby we are unable
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113439:21"/>
to write and print as we would againſt the adverſaries of the truth: it is hard to get our daily food with the labors of our weak bodies and feeble hands, how then ſhould we have to defray other charges, and to write and print? I have through the help of god out of his word, made a ſcourge of ſmall cords,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.2.</note> wherewith Antichriſt and his Miniſters might be driven one of the Temple of God. Alſo a declaration of certain falſe tranſlations in the new Teſtament; but I want wherewith to print and publiſh it, therefore it muſt reſt til the Lord ſee'th good to ſupply it.<note place="margin">It is the kings honor to ſearch out a thing Prov. 25. Exod 3.6.</note> In mean while, I humbly intreat his Majeſty and Parliament to give me leave to prove the Biſhops with one queſtion, by which you may perceive the ignorance of your Biſhops: 'tis this, how they will bee able to prove a reſurrection from theſe words, <hi>I am the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob.</hi> Onely from theſe words will they prove <hi>the reſurrection,</hi> if they be the Biſhops of Chriſt; for he proved the <hi>reſurrection from hence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 20.27.</note> The queſtion is hard I grant, but if their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips be not able to interpret it according to the meaning of Chriſt (as I am ſure they are not) then it will be another cauſe very ſufficient, for their deprivation from their Lordly and idol offices, and princely li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings. But becauſe moſt men do wreſt and miſ-interpret the Scriptures, ſome of wickedneſſe, and ſome of ignorance, for the utterance of their doctrines, and ſo deceive both Prince and people: I will ſhew how you ſhall perceive it, leſt thereby you ſtill be deceived Every Scripture ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore miſ-interpreted do make a contradiction: As for example M. <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> (one of the Preachers called Browniſts) to prove <hi>Rome</hi> a true church alledgeth 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. where the Apoſtle ſheweth, <hi>That the man of ſin, and ſon of perdition ſitteth in the Temple of God</hi>; which words, <hi>Temple of God,</hi> he interpreteth to be the church of God, whereby he doth greatly erre; for then ſuch interpretation will contradict this ſcripture which ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15</note> 
               <hi>The Church of God is the pillar and ground of truth.</hi> But if <hi>the man of ſin ſitteth there,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 28.2. Rev. 18 4.</note> 
               <hi>then it is a hold of foul ſpirits, a cage of every unclean and hatefull bird, as the Scripture ſpeaketh: yea, the pillar and ground of falſhood, and not of truth</hi>: Neither would the Lord call his people out of her (as he doth) if it were the true Church.<note place="margin">Rev. 12.13, 14.</note> Alſo, if the temple of God in that place be interpreted the church of God, this foul abſurdity and contradiction will follow, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Church (called the woman) to whom were given two wings of a great Eagle, that ſhe might fly into the wilderneſſe from her perſecutors, for a time, times, and half a time, was not perſecuted neither yet did ſly into the wilderneſſe ſo long a time. Neither yet was the Church (called both <hi>woman and whore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Re. 17.1, 5.</note> 
               <hi>alſo great Babylon, the mother of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113439:21"/>
whoredoms and abominations of the earth) drunken with the blood of the ſaints, and of the martyrs of Ieſus,</hi> as the Scripture teſtifyeth.</p>
            <p>Again, if that be the church of God, where the man of ſin ſitteth, then the winepreſſe was not troden without, but within the Church; and ſo it alſo croſſeth this Scripture, which ſaith,<note place="margin">Rev. 14.20.</note> 
               <hi>the winepreſs was troden without the City, ſo that blood came out unto the horſe bridles, by the ſpace of a thouſand and ſix hundred furlongs,</hi> Ergo <hi>a falſe interpretation.</hi> Moreover, we are not to underſtand the word <hi>Temple</hi> at all times to mean the Church; for when Chriſt ſaid, deſtroy this Temple, and in three days I will raiſe it up again, did not mean the church, nor yet the materiall Temple wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was, but meant his body, yet the Jews underſtood the word Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple otherwiſe, even as Mr. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> &amp;c doe here underſtand the word Temple otherwiſe, then the bodies of peoples, multitudes, nations,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.5.</note> and tongues, which they ought not to doe.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>If any man deſtroy the Temple of God, him will God deſtroy</hi>; did not mean the Church, but the members of the Church. So when he ſaid, <hi>the man of ſin ſitteth in the Temple of God,</hi> he did not mean ſo much as the members of the church, much leſſe the church. Therefore it muſt be underſtood, that all thoſe in whom the man of ſin ſitteth, are called the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> onely in reſpect that <hi>the Lord hath bought them,</hi> for the Lord hath bought all men,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1. 1 Joh. 2.2. 1 Cor. 6.19 20. &amp; 7.23. Lev. 18.6.</note> even <hi>the falſe teachers that deny him.</hi> Therefore no man is his own in that reſpect, but the Lords. Alſo the Biſhops themſelves (to prove brothers and ſiſters children may marry) alledge <hi>Lev.</hi> 18. But that Scripture do not prove ſuch marriages, but the full contrary for it ſaith, <hi>none ſhall come near to any of his kindred, to uncover ſhame.</hi> But brother and ſiſters children are kinsfolks:<note place="margin">Lev. 18.17.</note> therefore <hi>they may not come near to uncover ſhame, for that were wickedneſſe.</hi> This they muſt confeſſe, or elſe prove that brother and ſiſters children are not kinsfolks, which they cannot: ſeeing then, brother and ſiſters children cannot call cozen, and ſo all cozenſhip is blotted out by their doctrine, for uncles and Aunts call their brothers and ſiſters child, <hi>nephew</hi> &amp; <hi>neece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus many Biſhops and preachers do deceive Kings, Princes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples by wreſting and miſinterpreting the Scripture.<note place="margin">Col. 2.8.1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Therefore I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire your Majeſty and Parliament <hi>to beware, leſt there be any man that ſpoyle you, through Philoſophy and vaine deceit, through the Traditions of men, according to the rudiments of the World, and not after Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20, 21.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>And to avoid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and vain bablings and Antitheſis, or oppoſition, falſly called learning; which while ſome profeſſe, they have erred concerning the faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now O King, Prince and Parliament, open your eyes, and liſten
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113439:22"/>
your eares unto compaſſion and mercy:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10 Mat. 5.45. Ver. 21, 22. Lu. 18.7, 8. 2 Theſ. 14.8 Jam. 1.5, 6. Mat. 12.36.</note> fear God and be like unto him, for he <hi>cauſeth his ſun to ſhine both on juſt and unjuſt.</hi> Think at laſt you muſt give an account of your works: many at the day of judgemnt will bee ever burned for killing and burning innocent Chriſtians: but no man ſhall be damned for ſaving their lives; leane then I humbly beſeech you, on the right ſide of mercy, rather then yeeld unto ſuch as perſwade to perſecute innocent chriſtians: for they cannot help you, when you muſt give account therof unto Chriſt, who adviſeth you otherwiſe, although they be ſuch as erre, how much more ſuch as do but ſeem to err, and for difference in religion ought you to ſave their lives and I do in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity affirm,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.29.30, 39 Acts 17.31.</note> that thoſe which adviſe you to pluck up and burn the tares, (which <hi>Chriſt</hi> commands to be let alone till the end) doe adviſe you to pluck up and burn the commandement of Chriſt, unto whom aſſuredly (except amendment you ſhal give account at the day appointed. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleeve not ſuch as counſel you to ſhed blood for judgment in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: for if themſelves ſhould ſuffer the pain, they would verily give you other counſell, be not then their executioners any longer, for <hi>all that will live godly in Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12</note> 
               <hi>ſhall ſuffer perſecution,</hi> though you do your beſt to hinder it. And I pray to remember, that to preach the goſpel (after the mind of Chriſt) is to bring glad tydings unto the people; but to burn, baniſh, hang and impriſon for religion, is not to bring glad (but woful) tydings unto the people;<note place="margin">Luk. 2.10. Rom. 1.16.</note> let it not therefore bee any longer prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in your Majeſties dominions, I meekly intreat, <hi>Though Paul plans, and Apollos water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>yet it as God that giveth the encreaſe.</hi> But your Biſhops and Miniſters will have an increaſe whether God will or not, or elſe they will burn, baniſh, hang, and impriſon. Kings and Magiſtrates are Gods Miniſters and not the Biſhops; therefore I humbly beſeech you to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the bloudy minds of your Biſhops, that there be no more innocent Chriſtians perſecuted to death for Religion.<note place="margin">A crying ſin</note> I read that in the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands above a hundred thouſand perſons have been put to death for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but now praiſed be God we have no ſuch wofull tydings preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among us, the Lord work as much in our land I beſeech him, that ſo you may no longer burn and baniſh the ſervants of Chriſt; for he ſaith, <hi>they that do theſe things have not known the Father nor me</hi>:<note place="margin">Joh. 16.3.</note> yet I confeſſe you have the zeal of <hi>God,</hi> for you think you do <hi>God</hi> good ſervice in burning Chriſtians that differ from your Religion. But I alſo confeſſe your zeal is not according to knowledge for your Biſhops and Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indued with Univerſity and high ſchool learning,<note place="margin">Ro. 10.2, 3.</note> divinity and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but being ignorant of the lowly learning, heavenly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113439:22"/>
and doctrine of Chriſt, have and do ſtil go about to ſtabliſh their own and have not yet ſubmitted themſelves to the lowly learning, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity and doctrine of Chriſt: and therefore like their predeceſſors, wil perſwade you to burn, baniſh, &amp;c. ſuch Chriſtians as they hold to be in error about doctrines and queſtions of faith and Religion, right as if they had the power to rule, govern and diſpoſe the hearts and ſpirits of Kings, Princes and people, even as they liſt, and alſo to make them good and righteous when they will, and to cauſe them to underſtand and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the goſpel, even by a day and hour appointed, which to do, belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to God alone: and therefore Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.44.</note> 
               <hi>no man can come to me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Father draw him,</hi> and Chriſt will have his Miniſters to preach to ſuch as are worthy &amp; willing, and not as your Miniſters, who come to them whom they hold unworthy, and find unwilling, and ſay,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.11, 24.</note> 
               <hi>Will ye not come to church and hear, and will ye not beleeve our doctrine? but we wil make you, or elſe we will burn you for hereticks. Thus will they taunt meek and holy Chriſtians who are torn like ſheep among the wolves; but Chriſts miniſters will with meeknes inſtruct ſuch as are contrary minded, tolerating the evill men pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, proving if God at any time wil give them repentance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tit. 2.25. Ioh. 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>that they may know the truth: wherby they ſhew plainly that they are Chriſts diſciples,</hi> and have that true faith which worketh by love, even as the Apoſtle ſaith, the which I pray you to conſider, that ſo you may both know and obey the will of Chriſt. Now (ſaith he) <hi>abideth faith, hope and love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> 
               <hi>but the chiefeſt of theſe is love; for where love is there is no diſdaine, it ſeeketh not her own things, it is not provoked to anger, it ſuffereth all things, it hopeth all things, it indureth al things.</hi> Yea, the love of Chriſt ſo loveth, that it will not vex nor perſecute any that call on his name: therefore I humbly pray you to remember them <hi>that are in bonds, as though ye were bound with them; and them that are in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as if ye were alſo afflicted in the body; and to ſhew them mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>for mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth againſt judgment, but judgment mercileſſe ſhall be to them that ſhew no mercy. If ye be friendly to your brethren onely, what ſingular thing do you</hi>?<note place="margin">Iam. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>doe not the ſinners the ſame</hi>? be not like unto them,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.32, 37.</note> but unto your heavenly father whoſe wiſdom, love and mercy, I beſeech him to grant you, that ſo you may come to the knowledge of the truth and be ſaved: and that we your Majeſties faithfull ſubjects,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.</note> 
               <hi>may lead a peaceable and quiet life (even in our own nation) in all godlineſſe and honesty</hi>: Amen.</p>
            <p>Now, them that are perſecuted,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 4 12.</note> I exhort with the words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> Dearly beloved think it nor ſtrange concerning the fiery trial that is among you to prove you, as though ſome ſtrange thing were come unto you; but rejoyce, in as much as ye are partakers of Chriſts
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113439:23"/>
ſufferings, that when his glory ſhall appear, ye may be glad and rejoice. If ye be railed upon for the name of Chriſt, bleſſed are ye, for the ſpirit of glory and of God reſteth upon you,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 2.2.</note> which on their parts is evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, but on your part is glorified; but let no man ſuffer as an evil does or as a murtherer, or as a buſie body in others matters; but if one ſuffer as a Chriſtian,<note place="margin">Acts 24.14</note> let him not be aſhamed, but let him glorifie God in that behalf. For all the <hi>martyrs of the Apoſtolick Church have ſuffered as evill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and as hereticks.</hi> For the time is that judgment muſt muſt begin at the houſe of God: if it firſt begin at us (ſaith the Apoſtle) what ſhal the end be of them that obey not the goſpel of God: and if the righteous ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and ſinner appeare? wherefore let them that ſuffer according to the will of God, commit their ſouls unto him in weldoing, as unto a faithfull Creator.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Antichriſt and his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution ſhall bee made low. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Theſ. 2.4.</note>Read <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.2, 4, 11, 16.</p>
            <p>He ſhal judge among the nations, and rebuke many people, they ſhall break their ſword into mattocks, and their ſpears into ſithes: nations ſhall not lift up a ſword againſt nation, neither ſhall they learn to fight any more; the high lookes of man ſhall be humbled, and the loftineſſe of man ſhal be abaſed, and the Lord only ſhal be exalted in that day: for the day of the Lord of hoſts is upon all the proud and haughty, and upon all that is exalted, and it ſhall be made low.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Little</hi> David <hi>overcame great</hi> Goliah, <hi>yet not brought up in war:</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Peter <hi>confuted the learned Prieſts, yet by calling a Fiſherman. Attend and help,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.6. 1 Cor. 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>and you ſhall ſee the wonderfull works of God;</hi> For the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then men, and the weaknes of God is ſtronger then men: And God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and things that are deſpiſed hath God choſen, to bring to nought things that are, <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.25, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Leonard Buſher.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113439:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
